. >> ALL RIGHT.
GOOD AFTERNOON AND WELCOME TO THE JUNE 10TH, 2025 REGULAR
MEETING OF THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
>> MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL PLEASE?
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN PRESIDENT
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN PRESENT SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY
PRESENT SUPERVISOR ENGARDIO AND ENGARDIO PRESENTS
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER NOT PRESENT SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD
MAHMOOD PRESENT SUPERVISOR MANDEL MEN PRESENT MANDEL MEN
PRESENT SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR PRESENT SUPERVISOR HERR
SADR SADR PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHERYL SHERALD PRESENT
AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON PRESENT.
>> MR. PRESIDENT, DO YOU HAVE A QUORUM?
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS ACKNOWLEDGES THAT WE ARE THE ON THE UNCEDED
ANCESTRAL HOMELAND OF THE ROMITA COLONY WHO ARE THE
ORIGINAL INHABITANTS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO PENINSULA.
AS THE INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF THIS LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE
WITH THEIR TRADITIONS THE RAW MATERIALS WE HAVE NEVER CEDED
LOST NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE
CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO
RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL TERRITORY.
AS GUESTS WE RECOGNIZE THAT WE BENEFIT FROM LIVING AND WORKING
ON THEIR TRADITIONAL HOMELAND. WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY
ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS, ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE RAW
MATERIAL COMMUNITY AND BY AFFIRMING THEIR SOVEREIGN
RIGHTS AS FIRST PEOPLES. COLLEAGUES, WILL YOU JOIN ME
IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF ALLEGIANCE?
33 UNITED STATES TO THE REPUBLIC STANDS INDIVISIBLE
WITH LIBERTY AND JUSTICE. >> ON BEHALF OF OUR BOARD I
WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF AT S.F. GOV TV AND TODAY
ESPECIALLY KALEENA MENDOZA. THEY RECORD EACH OF OUR
MEETINGS AND MAKE THE TRANSCRIPTS AVAILABLE TO THE
PUBLIC ONLINE. >> WE'VE RECEIVED A
COMMUNICATION FROM SUPERVISOR FIELDER THAT SHE'S NOT GOING TO
BE ABLE TO ATTEND TODAY AND HAS REQUESTED TO BE EXCUSED.
CAN I HAVE A MOTION TO EXCUSE? SUPERVISOR FIELDER.
MOTION FROM CHEN SECONDED BY MAHMOOD.
MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE MOTION TO
EXCUSE SUPERVISOR FIELDER. >> SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR
EYES SUPERVISOR SUTTER SUTTER EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL
EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON. EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR AND GAUDIO AND GAUDIO EYES SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I AND SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI
MANAGEMENT I THERE ARE TEN EYES.
>> ALL RIGHT. WITHOUT OBJECTION SUPERVISOR
FIELDER IS EXCUSED FROM TODAY'S MEETING AND WITH THAT MADAM
CLERK CAN WE GO TO OUR 2 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER THE MAYOR'S
APPEARANCE AT THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
>> YES. SPECIAL ORDER AT 2 P.M. IS THE
APPEARANCE AT TODAY'S MEETING BY THE HONORABLE MAYOR DANIEL
LURIE PRESENT TO ENGAGE IN A FORMAL POLICY DISCUSSION WITH
ELIGIBLE BOARD MEMBERS PRIOR TO DISCUSSION THE MAYOR MAY
ADDRESS THE BOARD FOR UP TO FIVE MINUTES.
>> WELCOME, MR. MAYOR. THANK YOU.
>> DO YOU HAVE ANY OPENING REMARKS?
I DO WITH LIBERTY AND JUSTICE FOR ALL IS A GOOD WAY TO START
THIS MEETING. AS YOU ALL ARE AWARE, THERE ARE
IMMIGRATION ENFORCEMENT ACTIONS TAKING PLACE DOWNTOWN THIS
AFTERNOON. I KNOW THERE IS TREMENDOUS
ANXIETY AND FEAR IN COMMUNITIES ACROSS OUR CITY.
I KNOW YOU ALL FEEL THAT TOO BECAUSE THESE ARE OUR
COMMUNITIES. I WANT TO ASSURE THIS BOARD
AND EVERYONE IN SAN FRANCISCO THAT AS MAYOR MY GOAL IS TO
KEEP EVERYONE SAFE. I HAVE BEEN AND WILL CONTINUE
TO BE CLEAR THAT THESE FEDERAL IMMIGRATION ENFORCEMENT TACTICS
ARE INTENDED TO INSTILL FEAR AND THEY MAKE OUR CITY LESS
SAFE. I HAVE BEEN AND WILL EXCUSE ME
UNDER OUR CITY'S LONG STANDING POLICIES LOCAL LAW ENFORCEMENT
DOES NOT PARTICIPATE IN FEDERAL IMMIGRATION ENFORCEMENT.
THOSE ARE MY POLICIES AND OUR POLICIES AND THEY MAKE OUR CITY
SAFER. I AM COORDINATING WITH LOCAL
LAW ENFORCEMENT AND WE HAVE ACTIVATED OUR EMERGENCY
OPERATIONS CENTER. I'M ALSO IN TOUCH WITH
COMMUNITY LEADERS WHO ARE ON THE GROUND RIGHT NOW.
WE WILL CONTINUE THAT CLOSE COORDINATION SO THAT WE CAN
KEEP EVERYONE SAFE IN OUR CITY. I WANT TO THANK ALL OF YOU FOR
THE WORK YOU ARE DOING TO SUPPORT THOSE WHO ARE SCARED
AND WHO ARE STRUGGLING. I'M HERE TO SUPPORT YOU IN ANY
WAY THAT I CAN. AS WE KEEP OUR CITY SAFE EVERY
DAY THE WORK OF OUR CITY CONTINUES ACROSS OUR CITY EVERY
DAY. PEOPLE ARE LIVING IN RVS
AND OVERSIZE VEHICLES. IT AFFECTS OUR NEIGHBORHOODS,
PUBLIC SAFETY AND MOST IMPORTANTLY PEOPLE'S LIVES.
FAMILIES IN OUR CITY DESERVE BETTER OPTIONS AND OUR
NEIGHBORHOODS AND SMALL BUSINESSES DESERVE SAFE
AND CLEAN STREETS. NOW WE HAVE A COMPREHENSIVE
APPROACH THAT ACHIEVES BOTH OF THESE CRITICAL GOALS.
TODAY I AM INTRODUCING NEW LEGISLATION ALONG WITH
SUPERVISORS MELGAR SUPERVISOR AND BOARD PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN
SUPERVISOR AND GUARDIAN SUPERVISOR DORSEY
AND SUPERVISOR CHERYL TO TACKLE RV HOMELESSNESS WITH BOTH
ACTION AND COMPASSION. >> HERE'S WHAT IT DOES.
FIRST WE'RE PUTTING IN PLACE CITYWIDE PARKING LIMITS OF TWO
HOURS FOR OVERSIZE VEHICLES. THIS IS A NECESSARY STEP TO
ADDRESS A SIGNIFICANT IMPACT THESE VEHICLES HAVE ON OUR
PUBLIC SPACES. >> SECOND AND MORE CRUCIALLY,
WE ARE EXPANDING OUTREACH AND PRIORITIZING HOUSING
AND SERVICES NOT JUST ENFORCEMENT.
THIS IS CORE TO OUR APPROACH SIMPLY MOVING PEOPLE ALONG
ISN'T A SOLUTION. WE WILL RESTORE OUR STREETS
AND PUBLIC SPACES BUT WE WILL DO IT THE RIGHT WAY WITH
DIGNITY AND SUPPORT AND WITH REAL SOLUTIONS FOR THOSE
EXPERIENCING HOMELESSNESS. AND WE WILL DO IT IN A WAY THAT
BUILDS ON THE WORK WE'RE DOING UNDER THE BREAKING THE CYCLE
PLAN THAT INCLUDES A PROPOSAL THAT WE'VE INCLUDED IN OUR
BUDGET TO UNLOCK $90 MILLION OVER THREE YEARS TO
SIGNIFICANTLY EXPAND OUR INTERIM HOUSING CAPACITY.
THAT MEANS MORE BEDS AND SERVICES SPECIFICALLY
TARGETED TO THE NEEDS OF THOSE STRUGGLING ON OUR STREETS RIGHT
NOW. WE HAVE THE RESOURCES AND WE
CAN GIVE PEOPLE ON THE STREET A BETTER OPTION.
WE ALL KNOW THESE CHALLENGES ARE MULTIFACETED AND OUR
RESPONSE MUST BE AS WELL WITH COMPASSIONATE CARE, REAL
HOUSING ALTERNATIVES, SENSIBLE REGULATIONS AND REAL
ENFORCEMENT WITH EXPANDED COMPASSIONATE CARE AND HOUSING
OPTIONS WE CAN MAKE A REAL DIFFERENCE FOR OUR RESIDENTS
AND OUR NEIGHBORHOODS. I WANT TO THANK THE BOARD FOR
YOUR CONSIDERATION OF THIS LEGISLATION AND OF MY BUT
BUDGET PROPOSAL AND LOOK FORWARD TO ENGAGING IN THE DAYS
AND WEEKS AHEAD. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU MR. MAYOR, FOR THOSE REMARKS.
MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU PLEASE CALL THE FIRST TOPIC THE FIRST
TOPIC SUBMITTED BY THE DISTRICT TEN SUPERVISOR SHERMAN WALTON
IS SHELTER'S SUPERVISOR WALTON. >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
GOOD AFTERNOON, MR. MAYOR. OUR SHELTER SYSTEM IS IN URGENT
NEED OF PERMANENT SOLUTIONS TO ADDRESS HOMELESSNESS.
>> FAMILIES AND RESIDENTS IN MY DISTRICT HAVE SHARED THEIR
STRUGGLES UNHOUSED PERSONS HAVE BEEN PUSHED INTO SHELTER STAYS
THAT EXTEND FAR BEYOND TEMPORARY SOLUTIONS.
DISTRICT TEN HAS STEPPED UP IN MAJOR WAYS WITH THREE
NAVIGATION CENTERS AND NOW HOME TO AN UNSUPPORTED FORCED
UNILATERAL TINY HOME SITE ON GERALD.
WITH THE INTENTION OF INCREASING THE BLUEPRINT AT
GERALD AND THE BAYSHORE NAVIGATION CENTER WITHOUT
COMMUNITY BUY IN. AND YET THERE ARE OTHER AREAS
OF THE CITY WITH UNHOUSED POPULATION SIGNS AND NO PLANS
FOR SHELTER OR ANY TYPE OF HOMELESS SERVICES.
AT THE HEIGHT OF THE PANDEMIC IN ADDITION TO THREE NAVIGATION
CENTERS, DISTRICT TEN HOSTED A VEHICLE TRIAL SITE TO SAVE
SLEEPING SITES RV SITE AT PIER 94 AND THE VEO VEHICLE TRIAGE
CENTER. >> NO ONE CAN SAY THAT WE ARE
NOT DOING OUR FAIR SHARE IN DISTRICT TEN AS YOU MAKE
EFFORTS TO ADDRESS DOWNTOWN IN OTHER PARTS OF THE CITY.
MY DISTRICT HAS EVEN BEEN MORE IMPACTED THAN MANY OTHER
NEIGHBORHOODS IN SAN FRANCISCO. THESE PUSH OUTS OF OUR UNHOUSED
NEIGHBORS ACROSS THE CITY HAS RESULTED IN INCREASE NUMBER OF
UNHOUSED RESIDENTS IN DISTRICT TEN WITH NO REAL RESOURCES OR
STRATEGIES TO ADDRESS THIS. YOU COMMITTED TO WORKING WITH
ALL MY COLLEAGUES AND COMMUNITY WHEN YOU MAKE DECISIONS AND YET
THIS SUPERVISOR AND THE ENTIRE BAYVIEW COMMUNITY IS AGAINST
THE SHELTER ON GENERAL STREET BECAUSE YOU CHANGED THE
FOOTPRINT THAT WAS AGREED ON BY COMMUNITY.
YOU CONTINUE TO TRY AND GROW THE FOOTPRINT WITHOUT THE
SUPPORT OF ANYONE IN COMMUNITY. NO ONE IN THE AREA, NO ONE
IN BAYVIEW, NOT ONE BUSINESS AND NOT ONE RESIDENT SUPPORTS
THE SHELTER THAT IS IN PLACE. YOU CONTINUE TO SAY YOU WORK
WITH THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS IN GOOD FAITH BUT YET YOU
CONTINUE TO MAKE UNILATERAL DECISIONS IN AN AREA WITH TWO
NAVIGATION CENTERS IN CLOSE PROXIMITY.
MY QUESTION IS WILL YOU PAUSE THE PROPOSAL TO ADD BEDS TO THE
SITE ON JERROLD? OR WILL YOU CONTINUE TO
DISREGARD COMMUNITY VOICE AND PRETEND LIKE YOU WANT TO
WORK TOGETHER IN GOOD FAITH WHEN IN REALITY YOU MAKE
UNILATERAL DECISIONS AND STRESS LOW INCOME COMMUNITIES,
COMMUNITIES OF COLOR AND COMMUNITIES THAT DON'T HAVE
BIG POCKETS. >> MAYOR LURIE, YOU MAY RESPOND
TO THE OPENING QUESTION. I APPRECIATE THAT THE TONE
AND THE TENOR IN WHICH THE QUESTION WAS ASKED.
SUPERVISOR AND I ANSWER IT BROADLY AND CAN GET MORE
SPECIFIC. INTERIM HOUSING CAPACITY IS ONE
OF THE MOST URGENT AND HUMANE STEPS WE CAN TAKE AS A CITY TO
MEET THE NEEDS ON OUR STREETS. MY BREAKING THE CYCLE
INITIATIVE IS NOT JUST ABOUT CREATING ADDING OR JUST ADDING
CAPACITY. IT'S ABOUT PROVIDING THE RIGHT
TYPE OF BEDS TAILORED TO MEET THE SPECIFIC NEEDS OF DIFFERENT
POPULATIONS AND NEIGHBORHOODS. THE JERALD COMMON SITE
REPRESENTS A CRITICAL PART OF THAT EFFORT.
PHASE ONE OF GERALD COMMONS OPENED IN APRIL WITH 60 CABINS
FOR OLDER ADULTS STRUGGLING WITH HOMELESSNESS.
THE PROPOSED EXPANSION WILL ALLOW US TO ADD 82 MORE BEDS
FOR OLDER ADULTS LIVING ON THE STREETS.
THIS WILL HELP US ALLEVIATE STREET HOMELESSNESS IN THE
BAYVIEW AND SURROUNDING NEIGHBORHOODS.
THIS PROJECT IS A FIRST OF ITS KIND COLLABORATION BETWEEN US H
. DIAZ AND TO BRING ON MORE
NECESSARY CLINICAL SERVICES TO OUR SHELTERS.
THE THE DEPARTMENTS ARE WORKING WITH HOME BRIDGE AND IN-HOME
SUPPORTIVE SERVICES PROVIDER TO OFFER COMPREHENSIVE SUPPORT
AND CAREGIVING SERVICES TO MEET THE NEEDS OF OLDER ADULTS
STAYING IN THOSE CABINS. THEY WILL ALSO ASSESS OTHER
SUPPORTIVE SOCIAL SERVICES NEEDED TO EFFECTIVELY MOVE
GUESTS EXPERIENCING HOMELESSNESS INTO STABILITY.
THE CITY HAS ENGAGED IN A ROBUST COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT
PROCESS THAT BEGAN IN AUGUST OF 23 AND CONTINUES TODAY.
MY STAFF ALONG WITH H H MEETS EVERY OTHER WEEK WITH THE
MARKET ZONE WORKING GROUP TO ADDRESS COMMUNITY NEEDS
AND CONCERNS. THIS AREA IS IN NEED OF
INFRASTRUCTURE INVESTMENT AND THE COMMUNITY HAS
LEGITIMATE ASKS OF THE CITY. MY TEAM IS WORKING CLOSELY WITH
STAKEHOLDERS TO MAKE REQUESTED LIGHTING AND SAFETY
IMPROVEMENTS IN THE AREA AND WE WILL CONTINUE TO WORK CLOSELY
WITH COMMUNITY STAKEHOLDERS TO ENSURE THAT THIS PROJECT IS
SERVING THE COMMUNITY AND GIVING PEOPLE SLEEPING ON
OUR STREETS A BETTER OPTION. AS PART OF OUR WORK WITH
NEIGHBORS WE HAVE SET UP A PUBLIC PHONE LINE AT GERALD
COMMENTS THAT COMMUNITY MEMBERS CAN CALL IF THERE ARE ISSUES
WITH THE PROJECT. WE PUT THAT NUMBER ON FLIERS
AND SHARED IT AT COMMUNITY MEETINGS AND SINCE OPENING ON
APRIL THIRD WE HAVE NOT RECEIVED A SINGLE COMPLAINT
FROM THE COMMUNITY. THE CITY HAS BEEN WORKING WITH
THE COMMUNITY FOR TWO YEARS ON THIS PROJECT AND THAT WILL
CONTINUE BUT WE HAVE AN URGENT CRISIS ON OUR STREETS AND THOSE
WHO ARE STRUGGLING DESERVE HELP RIGHT NOW.
I BELIEVE WE CAN DO BOTH. SUPERVISOR.
THANK YOU MAYOR LURIE. SUPERVISOR WALTON YOU MAY ASK A
FOLLOW UP QUESTION DIRECTLY RELATED TO THE OPENING
QUESTION. >> THANK YOU PRESIDENT MADAM
AND MR. MAYOR. YOU DID NOT ANSWER MY QUESTION
. >> AGAIN, YOU MAY BE MEETING
WITH THE MARKET ZONE. YOU MAYBE HAVING CONVERSATIONS
WITH FOLKS IN THE AREA BUT NO ONE SUPPORTS IT.
AND THIS IS NOT JUST SUPERVISOR WALTON MAKING PLAYING MAKE
BELIEVE. EVERYONE IN THAT AREA DOES NOT
SUPPORT IT. YOU HAVE NOT ONE QUOTE IN YOUR
PRESS RELEASE FROM ANYBODY FROM THAT COMMUNITY NOT A RESIDENT,
NOT A BUSINESS BECAUSE NOBODY SUPPORTS IT.
SO YOU CAN COME HERE AND MISREPRESENT BECAUSE YOU'RE
HAVING CONVERSATIONS AND MAKE IT SEEM LIKE THERE'S COMMUNITY
SUPPORT BUT IT'S NOT. AND THEY MAY NOT BE COMPLAINING
TO YOU BUT THEY MOST CERTAINLY ARE COMPLAINING TO ME.
SO AGAIN, I'M GOING TO ASK YOU BECAUSE YOU CONTINUE TO CLAIM
THAT YOU WORK WITH SUPERVISORS ,THAT YOU WORK COLLABORATIVELY
BUT YOU UNILATERALLY PUT THIS SHELTER IN BAYVIEW.
YOU'RE UNILATERALLY TRYING TO PUT AN AMENDMENT ON BUDGET THAT
WILL INCREASE THE FOOTPRINT NOT ONLY AT JERALD BUT ALSO AT THE
BABY NAVIGATIONS IN HER AND IN SOME OF OUR CONVERSATIONS YOU
CLAIM THAT YOU WOULD LIKE TO ADDRESS HOMELESSNESS IN THE
AREAS WHERE WE SEE PEOPLE WHO ARE UNHOUSED BUT YET THERE'S
NOT A PROPOSED SHELTER BY THE BEACH.
THERE'S NOT A PROPOSED SHELTER BY GOLDEN GATE PARK.
THERE'S NOT A PROPOSED SHELTER BY LAKE MERCIER.
SO WILL YOU CONTINUE TO UNILATERALLY MAKE DECISIONS
ABOUT HOW WE ADDRESS HOMELESSNESS AN AREA'S ALREADY
STRESSED WITHOUT THE INPUT OF COMMUNITY.
>> I AM GOING TO WORK WITH COMMUNITY.
I MAKE CONTINUE TO BE OUT IN BAYVIEW.
WE CONTINUE TO WORK WITH OTHER SUPERVISORS AROUND PUTTING
SHELTERS THE RIGHT KIND OF SHELTER BEDS ALL OVER THIS
CITY. I BELIEVE THE RV LEGISLATION
THAT IS COMING FORWARD IS GOING TO HELP IMPROVE THE LIVES OF
BAYVIEW RESIDENTS AND I WILL CONTINUE TO BE IN COMMUNITY.
YOU KNOW, I'M OUT THERE OFTEN AND YOU AND I ARE GOING TO JUST
DISAGREE ON THE FACT THAT YOU SAY NOT ONE SINGLE PERSON
SUPPORTS IT BUT I AM HAPPY TO CONTINUE THE CONVERSATIONS.
I'M GOING TO DO WHAT I THINK IS BEST FOR SAN FRANCISCO AND FOR
ALL COMMUNITIES AND I THINK I'M DOING JUST THAT.
>> MAYOR LURIE, YOU MAY NOW ASK A QUESTION TO SUPERVISOR WALTON
OR ANY OTHER SUPERVISOR IN ATTENDANCE PERTAINING TO THE
SAME TOPIC BUT NOT NECESSARILY RELATED TO THE PREVIOUS
QUESTION. OKAY.
OKAY. >> THAT CONCLUDES THE DISTRICT
TEN TOPIC DISCUSSION. MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE
CALL THE NEXT TOPIC THE NEXT TOPIC SUBMITTED BY THE DISTRICT
11 SUPERVISOR CHEYENNE CHEN IS CENTERING COMMUNITY NEEDS
IN CAPITAL INVESTMENT PROJECTS. >> SUPERVISOR CHEN PLEASE ASK
YOUR OPENING QUESTION. >> THANK YOU, PRESTON AND GOOD
AFTERNOON, MR. MAYOR FROM DISTRICT 11 WE WANT TO KNOW
WHAT WHAT PROCESS ARE YOUR OFFICE IMPLEMENTING TO ENSURE
THAT MAJOR CAPITAL INVESTMENTS THAT ARE CURRENTLY UNDERWAY
IN HISTORIC LITTLE NEGLECTED PARTS OF OUR CITY ARE
RESPONSIVE TO COMMUNITY NEEDS AND PRIORITIES?
>> SPECIFICALLY SPEAKING, WHAT ARE YOU DOING TO MAKE SURE THAT
NEIGHBORHOOD NEEDS ARE BEING IDENTIFIED AND ADDRESS IN THE
GIANTS KRAKOA AMAZON RENOVATION INGLESIDE POLICE STATION OCEAN
WHEEL LIBRARY AND THE OTHER MAJOR PUBLIC PRIVATE CAPITAL
PROJECTS. >> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHEN I
APPRECIATE YOUR CONSISTENT ADVOCACY ON THIS TOPIC.
YOU AND I HAVE HAD MANY CONVERSATIONS ABOUT THIS
AND TALKS. THE INFRASTRUCTURE YOU
MENTIONED NOT ONLY SERVES DISTRICT 11 BUT THE ENTIRE
CITY. FIRST I WANT TO SAY ENSURING
MAJOR CAPITAL INVESTMENTS IN HISTORICALLY UNDERSERVED
NEIGHBORHOODS ARE RESPONSIVE TO COMMUNITY NEEDS IS A PRIORITY
FOR MY ADMINISTRATION. SAN FRANCISCO'S CAPITAL
PLANNING PROCESS IS DESIGNED WITH TRANSPARENCY AND EQUITY AT
ITS CORE. EVERY TWO YEARS THE CITY
DEVELOPS A TEN YEAR CAPITAL PLAN REVIEWED AND ADOPTED
THROUGH THE PUBLICLY NOTICED CAPITAL PLANNING COMMITTEE
MEETINGS AND APPROVED BY THE MAYOR AND BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
THIS PLAN PRIORITIZES INVESTMENTS THAT ADVANCE EQUITY
AND DIRECTLY RESPOND TO THE NEEDS OF VULNERABLE
COMMUNITIES. COMMUNITY INPUT ISN'T LIMITED
TO PLAN ADOPTION DEPARTMENTS ENGAGE IN LOCAL STAKEHOLDERS
THROUGHOUT PLANNING DESIGN AND CONSTRUCTION TO ENSURE
PROJECTS REFLECT NEIGHBORHOOD PRIORITIES.
LET ME TOUCH ON A COUPLE OF THE PROJECTS THE NEW INGLESIDE
POLICE STATION WILL INCLUDE 1250 SQUARE FOOT COMMUNITY ROOM
LOCATED PROMINENTLY NEAR THE ENTRANCE INTENDED NOT ONLY FOR
POLICE LED COMMUNITY MEETINGS BUT ALSO FOR YOUTH PROGRAMS,
SAFETY, EDUCATION AND NEIGHBORHOOD EVENTS
IN PARTNERSHIP WITH REC AND PARK.
THIS $109 MILLION INVESTMENT IS IS SLATED FOR COMPLETION
IN 2029. IN RESPONSE TO THE STRONG
COMMUNITY FEEDBACK, THE OCEAN VIEW LIBRARY SHIFTED FROM A
RENOVATION PLAN, AS YOU KNOW, TO A FULL REBUILD.
SINCE 2019 THE LIBRARY HAS CONDUCTED NUMEROUS PUBLIC
MEETINGS TO CO-CREATE A VISION WITH RESIDENTS.
$42 MILLION HAS BEEN ALLOCATED THROUGH FISCAL YEAR 26 AND THE
LIBRARY IS ACTIVELY EXPLORING SITE OPTIONS WITH REAL ESTATE
SERVICES AND WE WELCOME CONTINUED INPUT TO SHAPE THE
FUTURE OF THE FACILITY. ULTIMATELY OUR GOAL IS TO
ENSURE THAT CAPITAL PROJECTS ARE NOT JUST INVESTMENTS
IN INFRASTRUCTURE BUT IN COMMUNITY WELL-BEING.
I LOOK FORWARD TO CONTINUE TO WORK WITH YOU ALSO WITH THE
GIANTS ON CROCKER AMAZON AND I APPRECIATE YOUR SUPPORT
AND YOUR COLLABORATION ON THAT. >> THANK YOU, MAYOR.
LARRY SUPERVISOR CHEN YOU MAY NOW ASK A FOLLOW UP QUESTION
DIRECTLY RELATED TO THE OPENING QUESTION.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU, MR. MAYOR, FOR YOUR
RESPONSE. >> WE ARE ALSO HEARING FROM
CONSTITUENTS THAT DECIPHERS HAVING FULLY DELIVERED THE
NEEDED ACCESS TO PLANNING AND DESIGN PROCESS.
SO CAN I HAVE YOUR COMMITMENT THAT YOU WILL PRIORITIZE
WORKING TOGETHER WITH ME TO BE ALSO IN DISTRICT 11 TALKING TO
MY CONSTITUENTS AND OUR CONSTITUENTS ABOUT THIS MAJOR
INVESTMENTS THAT WILL IMPACT OUR FUTURE GENERATIONS?
>> ABSOLUTELY. THANK YOU.
ALL RIGHT. MAYOR LURIE, YOU MAY ASK A
QUESTION SUPERVISOR CHEN OR ANY OTHER SUPERVISOR IN ATTENDANCE
PERTAINING PERTAINING TO THE SAME TOPIC BUT NOT NECESSARILY
RELATED TO THE PREVIOUS QUESTION.
>> HE'S GOOD. ALL RIGHT.
THAT CONCLUDES THE DISTRICT 11 TOPIC DISCUSSION AND THE MATTER
HAS BEEN DISCUSSED AND WILL BE FILED AFTER GENERAL PUBLIC
COMMENT AND THEN WE GO BACK. >> MADAM CLERK, I THINK TWO
COMMUNICATIONS MEETING MINUTES. >> UH, COMMUNICATIONS.
OKAY. HERE WE GO.
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS WELCOMES YOU ALL TO ATTEND THIS MEETING IN THE
BOARD'S LEGISLATIVE CHAMBER WITHIN CITY HALL.
SECOND FLOOR, ROOM 250. IF YOU CAN'T MAKE IT TO THE
CHAMBER, YOU'RE ABLE TO WATCH CHANNEL 26.
THAT IS AS HAVE TV'S CHANNEL OR YOU CAN VIEW THE LIVE STREAM AT
W W W DOT SFD OF TV.ORG IF YOU HAVE PUBLIC COMMENT THAT YOU
WOULD LIKE TO SUBMIT TO THE BOARD YOU CAN EITHER SEND AN
EMAIL TO BOSSIE AT S F GOFORTH OR USE THE US POSTAL SERVICE
AND ADDRESS THE ENVELOPE TO THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS. THE NUMBER ONE DR. CARLTON B
GOODLATTE PLACE CITY HALL ROOM 244 SAN FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA
94102 IF YOU NEED TO EITHER MAKE A REASONABLE ACCOMMODATION
REQUEST UNDER THE AMERICANS WITH DISABILITIES ACT OR IF YOU
NEED TO REQUEST ANY LANGUAGES ASSISTANCE YOU CAN CONTACT THE
CLERK'S OFFICE AT LEAST TWO BUSINESS DAYS IN ADVANCE BY
CALLING (415) 554-5184. >> THANK YOU MEMBERS THANK YOU,
MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO APPROVAL OF OUR MEETING MINUTES
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. >> APPROVAL OF THE MAY 6TH,
2025 BOARD MEETING MINUTES IF ANYONE HAS ANY CHANGES.
I DON'T SEE ANYONE POPPING UP ON THE QUEUE SO CAN I HAVE A
MOTION TO APPROVE THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED MOVED BY CHEN
SECONDED BY CHERYL. MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL ON THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED?
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SARTOR SARDAR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO
AND ENGARDIO I SUPERVISOR MY WOULD MAHMOOD I AND SUPERVISOR
MANDOLIN I MANDAL ELMAN I THERE ARE TEN EYES ALL RIGHT WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE MINUTES WILL BE APPROVED AFTER PUBLIC COMMENT
AS PRESENTED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO OUR CONSENT TO OUR
CONSENT AGENDA ITEMS TWO THROUGH NINE ITEMS TWO THROUGH
NINE ARE ON CONSENT WHICH MEANS THAT THESE ITEMS ARE CONSIDERED
TO BE ROUTINE. IF A MEMBER OBJECTS AN ITEM MAY
BE REMOVED AND CONSIDERED SEPARATELY SEEING NO ONE ON THE
ROSTER MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE
CONSENT AGENDA ON ITEMS TWO THROUGH NINE SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON HI WALTON I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO ENGARDIO I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD
MAHMOOD I AND SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MENDELSON I THERE
ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THESE ORDINANCES ARE FINALLY
PASSED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO UNFINISHED BUSINESS ITEM NUMBER
TEN ITEM TEN THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO APPROPRIATE
APPROXIMATE LEE 7.9 MILLION OF AMBULANCE SERVICE REVENUE
IN THE FIRE DEPARTMENT AND TO APPROPRIATE APPROXIMATELY 1.5
MILLION IN PERMANENT SALARIES IN THE DEPARTMENT OF EMERGENCY
MANAGEMENT APPROXIMATELY SIX 866,000 IN THE FIRE DEPARTMENT
AND 500,000 IN THE PUBLIC UTILITIES COMMISSION AND TO
APPROPRIATE APPROXIMATELY 3.7 MILLION TO PERMANENT SALARIES
AND APPROXIMATELY 5 MILLION TO OVERTIME IN THE FIRE DEPARTMENT
APPROXIMATELY 1.5 MILLION TO OVERTIME IN THE DEPARTMENT OF
EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT AND 500,000 TO OVERTIME IN THE
PUBLIC UTILITIES COMMISSION IN ORDER TO SUPPORT THE
DEPARTMENT'S PROJECTED INCREASES IN OVERTIME IN FISCAL
YEARS 2024 THROUGH 2025. AND MR. PRESIDENT, THIS
ORDINANCE REQUIRES A TWO THIRDS VOTE OF ALL MEMBERS OF THE
BOARD FOR APPROVAL OF THE FIRE DEPARTMENT'S APPROPRIATION OF
APPROXIMATELY 7.9 MILLION. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
LET'S TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 11.
ITEM 11 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE
TO ESTABLISH AND DEFINE THE MEMBERSHIP AND DUTIES OF THE
BOARD OF DIRECTORS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO DOWNTOWN
REVITALIZATION AND ECONOMIC RECOVERY FINANCING DISTRICT
AND WILL TAKE THIS SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
ORDINANCES PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL
ITEM 12 ITEM 12 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AUTHORIZE THE
CLERK OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS TO SELL LICENSES TO
THIRD PARTIES TO LEGISLATIVE MANAGEMENT SYSTEM SOFTWARE
DEVELOPED BY THE CLERK'S OFFICE AND TO AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE
CODE TO ESTABLISH A FUND TO RECEIVE REVENUE FOR LICENSING
THE LEGISLATIVE MANAGEMENT SYSTEM SOFTWARE TO THIRD
PARTIES AND FROM INTER-DEPARTMENTAL FUND
TRANSFERS FROM CITY DEPARTMENTS TO USE FOR THE LEGISLATIVE
MANAGEMENT SYSTEM WILL TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 13 ITEM 13 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO
APPROVE A SECOND AMENDMENT TO THE GRANT AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE
SAN FRANCISCO ADULT PROBATION DEPARTMENT AND THE REGENTS OF
THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA ON BEHALF OF ITS SAN FRANCISCO
CAMPUS FOR CASE MANAGEMENT SERVICES TO INCREASE THE GRANT
AMOUNT BY APPROXIMATELY 7.76 MILLION FOR A NEW TOTAL OF 17.1
MILLION AND TO EXTEND THE GRANT TERM BY TWO YEARS FROM JUNE
30TH 2025 FOR A NEW TOTAL TERM THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2027 AND WILL
TAKE THIS SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM
14. >> ITEM 14 THIS IS A RESOLUTION
TO APPROVE A PORT COMMISSION LEASE WITH 340 JEFFERSON STREET
PARTNERS LLC FOR APPROXIMATELY 3750FT2 OF A SINGLE STORY
RESTAURANT SPACE LOCATED AT 340 JEFFERSON STREET FOR TEN YEARS
WITH A25 YEAR OPTIONS TO EXTEND AND TO ESTIMATE TO PRODUCE
APPROXIMATELY 1.5 MILLION IN REVENUE OVER THE TEN YEAR
TERM WITH THE PORT CONTRIBUTING 470,000 FOR IMPROVEMENTS TO THE
PREMISES WILL TAKE THIS SAME HOUSE SAME CALL.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 15.
ITEM 15 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO APPROVE THREE DIRECT CURRENT
FAST CHARGING HUB LEASE WITH SKY CHARGERS LLC AND THE CITY
FOR A 14 YEAR TERM WITH ONE TWO YEAR OPTION TO EXTEND AND A
MINIMUM ANNUAL GUARANTEE OF 190,000 FOR THE FIRST YEAR OF
THE LEASE. >> AND AGAIN SAME HOUSE, SAME
CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED AND MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO OUR 230
SPECIAL ORDER. >> YES IT IS NOW 230 AND TIME
FOR THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS TO APPROVE THE RECOGNITION OF
COMMENDATION FOR MERITORIOUS SERVICE TO THE CITY AND COUNTY
OF SAN FRANCISCO. >> AND FIRST UP DISTRICT SEVEN
SUPERVISOR MELGAR, THANK YOU SO MUCH PRESIDENT MANDO MAN TODAY
I I'M EXCITED TO HONOR THE STUDENT ORGANIZERS OF CECILIA'S
CHURCH AND SCHOOLS SOCKS, SHOES AND SWEATS DONATION DRIVE IF
YOU COULD PLEASE COME UP I APPRECIATED SO MADELYN MOWBRAY
PATRICK JAMES MCCAULEY, GIANNA MONK REESE ROLAND AVA
AND ALEXANDRA GONZALEZ LIAM KEARNEY AND MARY SINUS
AND THEIR ADVISOR JEAN ROLAND AT THIS DONATION DRIVE WAS LED
BY THIS GROUP OF SEVENTH AND EIGHTH GRADERS FROM ST
CECILIA'S MAKING THIS THE FOR THE SCHOOL'S FIRST EVER STUDENT
RUN COMMUNITY SERVICE PROJECT. THIS DONATION DRIVE RAN THROUGH
THE MONTH OF MARCH AND DURING THAT TIME THE STUDENT LEADERS
WORKED REALLY HARD TO SPREAD THE WORD AND ENCOURAGE
DONATIONS. THEY MADE ANNOUNCEMENTS
IN THEIR SCHOOL AND PARISH THE COMMUNITY NEWSLETTERS WEEKLY
ANNOUNCEMENTS AFTER SUNDAY MASS MADE PRESENTATIONS FOR THEIR
DONATION DRIVE ON THEIR SCHOOL TV PLATFORM AND AT THE END OF
THE DONATION DRIVE THEY SENT OUT LOVELY THANK YOU LETTERS TO
EVERYONE IN THE COMMUNITY. THEY WERE ALWAYS UP FOR THE
ORGANIZATIONAL TASKS MAKING SURE TO CHECK ON THE COLLECTION
BARRELS AND WORKING HARD ON THE LAST DAY TO SORT AND RECORD
MANY OF THE DONATIONS. >> INITIALLY THE STUDENTS
PLANNED TO JUST HOST A SOCK DRIVE FOR THE UNHOUSED BUT ONCE
THEY CONNECTED WITH ST ANTHONY'S FOUNDATION THEY
DISCOVERED THAT MANY OTHER ITEMS WERE ALSO NEEDED.
SO THEY DECIDED TO EXPAND THEIR COLLECTION TO DONATIONS OF
IN ADDITION TO THAT SHOES AND SWEATPANTS THIS WILLINGLY
THIS WILLINGNESS TO REACH OUT LEARN WHAT WAS NEEDED AND ADAPT
THEIR PROJECT BASED ON FEEDBACK IS REALLY ADMIRABLE.
>> WELL IT SHOWS FLEXIBILITY AND CREATIVITY.
IT ALSO LED TO AN INCREDIBLY SUCCESSFUL DONATION DRIVE
IN WHICH STUDENTS COLLECTED MANY ESSENTIALS FOR THE
UNHOUSED INCLUDING 1521 PAIRS OF SOCKS, 49 PAIRS OF
SWEATPANTS AND 47 PAIRS OF SHOES.
OTHER DONATION ALSO COLLECTED INCLUDED SWEATSHIRTS, SHIRTS,
BAGS, MASKS, GLOVES AND FOOD AFTER DONATIONS WERE COLLECTED
THE ITEMS WERE GIVEN TO SAINT ANTHONY'S FOUNDATION TO BE
DISTRIBUTED TO PEOPLE IN NEED. >> THE STUDENTS DETERMINATION
TO ORGANIZE AND RUN THIS PROJECT THEMSELVES DEMONSTRATES
AN EXEMPLARY COMMITMENT TO COMMUNITY SERVICE.
THANK YOU ALL FOR EVERYTHING THAT YOU'VE DONE AND THANK YOU
FOR IT. UP BEING AMAZING STUDENTS FOR
STEPPING UP FOR MAKING THE EFFORT TO SERVE YOUR COMMUNITY
AND OF COURSE THANK YOU TO JEAN ROLL AND YOUR WONDERFUL PROJECT
ADVISOR. YOUR WORK HAS MADE AN IMPACT
AND NO DOUBT HELPED MANY PEOPLE AND WE NEED MORE HELP
AND HUMANITY IN THIS WORLD RIGHT NOW.
MAY YOUR PASSION TO SERVE AND NEVER WANE AND MAY THIS
SERVE AS AN INSPIRATION TO OTHER YOUNG LEADERS AND ADULTS
FRANKLY ABOUT WHAT CAN BE DONE IN SERVICE TO OTHERS.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR BEING HERE RIGHT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR METZGER PRESIDENT
MENDELSOHN AND THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS FOR INVITING US
HERE TODAY. MY NAME IS PATRICK MCCAULEY
AND I ALONG WITH A FEW OTHER JUNIOR HIGH STUDENTS FROM SAINT
CECILIA HAVE WORKED HARD TO ORGANIZE AND PARTICIPATE IN A
DONATION DRIVE TO BENEFIT SAINT ANTHONY'S THIS DRIVE MEANT A
LOT TO US AND WE'RE EXTREMELY HONORED TO BE HERE TODAY TO
RECEIVE A CERTIFICATE OF RECOGNITION.
>> MY NAME IS OMRI SILAS. WE VOLUNTEERED TO DO THIS
PROJECT BECAUSE WE WANTED TO GAIN EXPERIENCE AND LEADERSHIP
LITERATURE RESPONSIBILITY OF THE SAN FRANCISCO COMMUNITY
AND HELP GRIFFITHS. >> MY NAME IS ALEX GONZALEZ.
WE LEARNED THAT SAINT ANTHONY'S FOUNDATION ISSUES SWEATPANTS
AND SOCKS PARTICULARLY FOR MEN. THE PURPOSE OF THE DONATION
DRIVE WAS TO BRING OUR COMMUNITY TOGETHER
AND CONTRIBUTE BOTH DONATIONS AND TIME TO MEET THIS NEED FOR
THOSE WHO ARE LESS FORTUNATE. >> MY NAME IS REESE ROLAND
IN THE TENDERLOIN STRUGGLE WITH POVERTY ADDICTION AND MENTAL
ILLNESS. SAINT ANTHONY'S FOUNDATION HAS
BEEN A BEACON OF CONSISTENCY, COMPANIONSHIP AND CARING FOR 75
YEARS. THEY PROVIDE A RANGE OF
SERVICES INCLUDING INCLUDING CLOTHING, HOT MEALS, ADDICTION
RECOVERY, MEDICAL CARE, WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT, WOMEN
AND CHILDREN'S SERVICES AND THE PLACE TO REST.
>> SAINT ANTHONY'S TAKES A DIFFERENT APPROACH ONE THAT
DELIVERS MEANINGFUL RESULTS HOPE STABILITY, RENEWAL.
>> MY NAME IS JOHN MUNGAI AND WE'D ALSO LIKE TO THANK
SAINT SICILY A CHURCH AND SCHOOL FOR GIVING US THIS
OPPORTUNITY TO GIVE BACK TO OUR COMMUNITY.
I WANT TO RECOGNIZE ADDITIONAL MEMBERS OF OUR TEAM.
MADALINE MABRY, EVA ANDO AND LIAM KEARNEY.
THANK YOU AGAIN BOARD OF SUPERVISORS FOR THIS HONOR OF
RECOGNITION. GOOD JOB EVERYBODY.
>> DISTRICT TEN SUPERVISOR WALTON.
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. COLLEAGUES, TODAY IT IS MY
HONOR TO CELEBRATE MAC ALLEN AFFECTIONATELY KNOWN AS MAC.
>> MAC IS A BELOVED MUNI TRANSIT OPERATOR WHO CURRENTLY
SERVES OUT OF THE WOODS DIVISION LOCATED IN THE
DOGPATCH AREA OF SAN FRANCISCO. MAC WAS BORN AND RAISED IN LAS
CRUCES, NEW MEXICO AND MOVED TO SAN FRANCISCO IN 2011 TO STUDY
ARCHITECTURE. FROM THE VERY BEGINNING HE FELT
A DEEP CONNECTION TO THE CITY AND QUICKLY KNEW HE HAD FOUND A
HOME. IT WAS HERE HE MET HIS WIFE
HOLLY AT CAFE DU NORD. THE COUPLE MARRIED AT CITY HALL
IN 2007 AND NOW RAISED THEIR TWO CHILDREN AGES 15 AND 13
IN THE SAME DOGPATCH NEIGHBORHOOD WHERE MAC BEGINS
AND ENDS HIS DAILY MUNI ROUTES .
SINCE JOINING THE MTA IN 2021, MAC HAS BECOME FAMILIAR AND AN
UPLIFTING PRESENCE FOR MANY RIDERS.
HE CURRENTLY OPERATES THE 44 O'SHAUGHNESSY AND 37 CORBETT
LINES WHERE HE IS KNOWN NOT JUST FOR HIS SKILL BEHIND THE
WHEEL BEFORE HIS WARMTH, ATTENTIVE ATTENTIVENESS
AND UNMISTAKABLE JOY. HE BRINGS TO EACH RIDE MAC AS A
POET AT HEART OFFERING WRITING ABOUT MUNI AND SAN FRANCISCO.
HE IS A TWO TIME CHAMPION OF MUNI DIARIES LIVE A LOCAL
STORYTELLING AND POETRY EVENT. HIS WORDS REFLECT THE HUMANITY,
HUMOR AND SOUL OF EVERYDAY CITY LIFE AND HIS MISSION IS CLEAR
TO RAISE THE PROFILE OF PUBLIC TRANSIT AND THE PEOPLE WHO HELP
MAKE IT RUN. PARENTS FROM COMMUNITY HAVE
SHARED WITH OUR OFFICE HOW TOUCH THEY WERE WHEN MAC HANDED
OUT DRAWINGS AND HANDWRITTEN CARDS TO STUDENTS WHO REGULARLY
RIDE THE 44 LINE. THIS IS GOING ABOVE AND BEYOND
THESE SMALL ACTS OF KINDNESS AND CREATIVITY.
SPEAK VOLUMES ABOUT THE IMPACT HE HAS BEYOND HIS DUTIES AS A
DRIVER. HE IS NOT JUST A TRANSIT
OPERATOR BUT A DEEPLY WOVEN PART OF THE COMMUNITY AND A
FEATURE PUBLISHED BY MISSION LOCO.
MAC SHARED HIS REFLECTIONS ON THE MEANING OF HIS WORK.
HE SPOKE ABOUT HOW MUCH IT LIFTS HIS SPIRITS TO RECEIVE
COMMENDATIONS FROM PASSENGERS, ESPECIALLY KNOWING THAT MANY
OPERATORS NEVER RECEIVE SUCH RECOGNITION.
EARLIER THIS YEAR MAC LED A HEARTFELT EFFORT TO BRING
ATTENTION TO TRANSIT OPERATOR APPRECIATION DAY ON MARCH 18TH.
HIS GOALS WERE AMBITIOUS TO INCREASE RIDERSHIP BY 10%
AND TO COLLECT 500 COMMENDATIONS FOR FELLOW
OPERATORS ACROSS THE CITY. FOR MAC IT WAS ABOUT SUPPORTING
HIS COLLEAGUES AND HELPING SAN FRANCISCANS SEE THE PEOPLE
BEHIND THE WHEEL WITH NEW APPRECIATION.
MAC'S LOVE FOR PUBLIC TRANSIT BEGAN DURING WHAT MANY REMEMBER
AS THE MUNI MELTDOWN SUMMER OF 2018.
THAT YEAR AFTER WIDESPREAD SERVICE DISRUPTIONS, HE AND HIS
CHILDREN TOOK ON SOME CHALLENGE OF RIDING EVERY MUNI LINE
IN THE CITY. THE EXPERIENCE WAS BOTH
FRUSTRATING AND INSPIRING AND IT SPARKED THE IDEA THAT HE
COULD CONTRIBUTE TO MAKING THE SYSTEM BETTER BY BECOMING AN
OPERATOR HIMSELF. NEARLY FOUR YEARS INTO HIS
SERVICE, THEIR LOVE IS AS STRONG AS EVER.
MAC HAS A SPECIAL CONNECTION TO THE STUDENTS FROM REALLY BROWN
MIDDLE SCHOOL WHO RIDE HIS ROUTE EVERY AFTERNOON.
HE WATCHES OUT FOR THEM AS IF THEY WERE HIS OWN CHILDREN
AND THEY HAVE COME TO COUNT ON HIS STEADY AND FAMILIAR
PRESENCE EVEN IN THE FACE OF BUDGET CHALLENGES AND POTENTIAL
SERVICE CUTS BEING DISCUSSED ALL THE TIME.
MAC REMAINS HOPEFUL AND COMMITTED.
HE IS A REMINDER THAT EVERY MUNI LINE IS MORE THAN A ROUTE
IT IS A LIFELINE RUN BY SOMEONE WHO CARES DEEPLY ABOUT SAN
FRANCISCO AND HIS FUTURE. ONE OF MAC'S PROFESSIONAL GOALS
IS TO OPERATE AS A FIRM TO HIS ICONIC F LINE WHICH RUNS ALONG
MARKET STREET AND OUT TO FISHERMAN'S WHARF.
HE CARRIES A SINCERE ASPIRATION TO UPLIFT PUBLIC TRANSIT IN SAN
FRANCISCO NOT ONLY THROUGH EXCELLENT SERVICE BUT THROUGH
ART ADVOCACY AND EVERYDAY ACTS OF KINDNESS.
>> WE ARE PROUD TO HONOR MAC ALLEN, A POET AND ADVOCATE A
NEIGHBOR AND A TRUE STALWART OF SAN FRANCISCO'S PUBLIC LIFE.
>> THANK YOU FOR ALL THAT YOU DO.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH. SUPERVISOR WALTON PRESIDENT
MANAGEMENT BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
I'M EXTREMELY HONORED TO BE RECOGNIZED HERE TODAY.
I'LL KEEP MY STATEMENT VERY BRIEF AND I'LL READ MY POEM
THAT I SHARED WITH THE WILLIE BROWN STUDENTS.
I WANT TO EXTEND MY GRATITUDE BOTH TO SUPERVISOR WALTON
AND THE SCHOOL COMMUNITY OF WILLIE BROWN MIDDLE SCHOOL, THE
TEACHERS, STAFF, ADMINISTRATORS AND PARENTS WHO ARE DOING
SOMETHING REALLY SPECIAL OVER THERE.
MOST OF ALL I WANT TO THANK THE WILLIE BROWN STUDENTS WHO HAVE
BEEN RIDING MY BUS THIS LAST SCHOOL YEAR.
THEY'RE AWESOME KIDS A JOY TO SERVE AND I EXPECT THAT THEY
WILL CONTINUE TO MAKE US PROUD FOR YEARS TO COME.
I LOVE MUNI IN SAN FRANCISCO AND I WISH TO REMIND THIS BOARD
THAT OUR PUBLIC TRANSIT SYSTEM NEEDS TO BE PROPERLY FUNDED TO
MEET THE NEEDS OF THIS COMMUNITY.
>> FURTHERMORE NO HUMAN BEING IS ILLEGAL.
ABOLISH ICE. THIS IS MY POEM FOR THE 44
O'SHAUGHNESSY WILLIE BROWN STUDENTS RUN 174I SIGNED ON
1174 FROM THE BANK OF LAKE YELLOWSTONE 129 ON THE 44 WITH
SATURDAYS OFF. LOOKED GOOD IN PRINCIPLE AND I
TOOK IT THAT FIRST MONDAY AT SILVER AND REVERE AT 404 AS A
THRONG OF KIDS SWARMED MY BUS. I THOUGHT ONE SEVEN 4TH MAY
HAVE BEEN A MISTAKE ROLLING UP TO WILLIE BROWN MIDDLE RIGHT
AFTER SCHOOL EVERY DAY. MY BUS WOULD BE PACKED FRONT TO
BACK TOP TO BOTTOM. LUCKY IF THE DOORS CLOSE A
COACH LOAD OF MIDDLE SCHOOLERS MIGHT BE A NIGHTMARE BUT THIS
CREW WON MY HEART WITHIN THE WEEK AS I PULLED UP HORN
BEEPING A LITTLE TEARY. THE KIDS ARE CHEERING FOR THE
BUS AND THAT'S ALL IT TAKES. I'M A ROCK STAR STEPPING ON
STAGE AS THE CROWD ROARS AND WHEN THE KIDS RUSH THE BUS
IT'S AS THRILLING AS A WAVE BREAKING AT MAVERICKS AND SCARY
EVERY TIME I SWING OPEN THE DOORS AND GREET THEM IN THE
CUSTOMARY MANNER. NO PUSHING, NO RUNNING.
NO PUSHING. WELL, THEY PUSH AND RUN
AND FIND THEIR PLACE ON MY BUS .
I HIT THE BUTTONS THAT SAY I'M DROP OFF ONLY BROOKLYN DAD
ALWAYS THE LAST TO BOARD SQUEEZES IN.
WE DAP UP AND GO WITHIN THE WEEK THE KIDS FROM WILLIE BROWN
MIDDLE BECOME MY KIDS AND I'D NEVER WANT TO MISS THIS TRIP
CAN'T BEAR THINKING OF THEM WAITING AT THE CURB AND NO BUS
COMING. >> NOT ON MY WATCH SO IT WAS
AWFUL UNDERSTAND THAT DAY. THE OPERATOR I BELIEVE SENDS A
MESSAGE IS BLOCKED ON SILVER BY TOPEKA COPS AT THE SCHOOL WITH
GUNS DRAWN. EVERY PARENT IN AMERICA CAN
FEEL THE PANIC GRIPPING THE EDGES OF THOSE WORDS A PIP ON
THE MAP OF THE CRIME APP. POSSIBLE GUNMEN CENTERED ON THE
CAMPUS. THOSE ARE MY KIDS IN THERE.
AND IF ONLY I COULD BY MAGIC BRING THEM TO ME ON THAT DINGY
CORNER BY THE MACHINE SHOP WHERE OPERATORS SWAP SEATS.
THE RELIEF I WOULD HAVE FELT AT THAT POINT UNDERSTAND IT WAS
AWFUL. >> IT RESOLVED HAPPILY.
NO ONE WAS HURT AND NO SHOTS FIRED.
THE COPS WEREN'T EVEN AT THE SCHOOL.
THEY WERE NEXT DOOR STUPIDLY DOING AN ARMED HOUSE RAID AT
LUNCH HOUR ON A SCHOOL DAY. SO I PULLED UP BEEPING THAT
AFTERNOON AND MY KIDS ARE ALL THERE SHOUTING AND SMILING
AND RUSHING THE BUS LIKE THEY'LL LIVE FOREVER.
I TOOK THEM AWAY FROM SILVER IN REVERE.
I LEARNED BITS AND PIECES. THEY WERE LOCKED DOWN AND IT'S
LIKE THEY PRACTICED BUT NOTHING HAPPENED.
BROOKLYN DAD AND I COMPARE NOTES HOW THE HAIR STANDS UP ON
YOUR NECK. ALL YOU CAN THINK IS WHAT DO I
DO? WHO DO I CALL?
HOW DO I GET THERE? MY KIDS ARE ON MY BUS NOW AND I
DON'T WANT TO LET THEM OFF AT SAN BRUNO OR MISSION OR GLEN
PARK. I WANT TO TAKE THEM TO THE
BEACH AND BUY THEM ICE CREAM. OF COURSE I CAN'T.
SO I'LL DO THE ONE THING I CAN. LIKE I ALWAYS DO.
I'LL CALL OUT THE STOPS. I'LL OPEN THE DOORS.
CLOSE THE DOORS. ROLL THE COACH DOWN THE HILL.
THE ONE THING I CAN DO. >> I'LL TAKE THEM HOME
. >> DISTRICT FIVE SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD MR. TAKASHI ONISHI CAN UPSTAGE COLLEAGUES TODAY I HAVE
THE DEEP HONOR OF RECOGNIZING A MAN WHOSE INFLUENCE ON JAPAN
TOWN'S CULTURAL AND COMMERCIAL LIFE HAS SPANNED GENERATIONS
AND WHOSE PASSION FOR STORYTELLING HELPED INTRODUCE
AN ENTIRE COUNTRY TO A NEW WAY OF SEEING THE WORLD.
WE ARE HERE TO COMMEND THE REMARKABLE LEGACY OF MR.
TAKASHI ONISHI, THE FOUNDER OF JAPAN VIDEO AND MEDIA A PIONEER
OF ANIME AND MANGA IN AMERICA AND A STEADFAST STEWARD OF
JAPAN TOWNS, TRADITIONS, FESTIVALS AND COMMUNITY LIFE.
FOR MORE THAN FOUR DECADES WE ARE HERE BECAUSE THIS PAST MAY
AFTER 40 YEARS OF BUSINESS JAPAN FOUND JAPAN VIDEO
AND MEDIA CLOSED ITS DOORS FOR THE LAST TIME.
>> THIS COMMENDATION THEN IS BOTH A THANK YOU AND A TRIBUTE
TO A LEGACY THAT SHAPED NOT ONLY A NEIGHBORHOOD BUT A
GENERATION. >> MR. ONISHI DIDN'T JUST SELL
STORIES HE BUILT A SANCTUARY FOR IMAGINATION A HAVEN FOR
SUBCULTURES AND A LANDMARK WHERE SAN FRANCISCO'S YOUTH
FAMILIES AND ARTISTS COULD GATHER, LEARN AND DREAM.
>> WHEN I FIRST LEARNED OF MR. ONISHI STORY I EXPECTED TO HEAR
EXCLUSIVE ONLY ABOUT HIS WORK IN CREATING A ROBUST DVD
AND VHS SELECTION FOR HIS CUSTOMERS.
WHAT I DIDN'T EXPECT THOUGH I SHOULD HAVE WAS JUST HOW DEEPLY
PERSONAL HIS IMPACT HAD BEEN. >> I HEARD ABOUT PEOPLE WHO
GREW UP VISITING JAPAN VIDEO EVERY WEEKEND CHILDREN WHO ARE
NOW ARTISTS ANIMATORS, TEACHERS AND PARENTS THEMSELVES.
>> I HEARD ABOUT THE CELEBRITIES WHO QUIETLY
FREQUENTED THE STORES INCLUDING ROBIN WILLIAMS, JOE MONTANA
BRINGING THEIR KIDS TO EXPLORE A WORLD UNLIKE ANY OTHER.
>> BUT MOST OF ALL I HEARD ABOUT MR. ONISHI HIS HEART, HIS
GENEROSITY, HIS CURIOSITY, HIS BELIEF THAT CULTURE COULD CROSS
OCEANS, GENERATIONS AND GENRES AND STILL FEEL LIKE HOME.
>> WHEN MR. NISHI FOUNDED JAPAN VIDEO IN THE 1980S, ANIME
AND MANGA WERE VIRTUALLY UNKNOWN IN THE UNITED STATES.
>> BLOCKBUSTER DIDN'T CARRY IT NO LONGER DOES EITHER.
AMAZON DIDN'T EXIST AND YET MR. NISHI BELIEVED FIERCELY THAT
THERE WAS AN AUDIENCE HERE. >> HE CURATED IMPORTED,
SUBTITLED AND EVANGELIZED A GENRE THAT WOULD GO ON TO SHAPE
A GLOBAL POP CULTURE BEFORE MANY OTHERS DID.
JAPAN VIDEO WASN'T JUST A STORE IT WAS A GATEWAY FOR THOUSANDS
OF CUSTOMERS. IT WAS THE FIRST PLACE THEY
ENCOUNTERED TITLES LIKE AKIRA OR SAILOR MOON ONE OF WHICH I
HAVE SEEN AND THE OTHER I HAVE NOT.
>> BEFORE THEY WERE HOUSEHOLD NAMES MR. ONISHI GAVE PEOPLE
ACCESS TO STORIES THEY DIDN'T EVEN KNOW THEY WERE LOOKING
FOR. AND IN DOING SO HE HELPED
CREATE A WHOLE NEW FAN BASE ONE CUSTOMER AT A TIME.
>> IN 2020 HIS VISION AND IMPACT WERE OFFICIALLY
RECOGNIZED IN SAN FRANCISCO'S LEGACY BUSINESS DESIGNATION A
REMINDER THAT CULTURE MEMORY LIKE ANY LANDMARK DESERVES A
PRESERVATION. >> BEYOND THE STOREFRONT, MR.
NISHI WAS A CORNERSTONE OF JAPANTOWN CIVIC LIFE.
HE SERVED AS A MEMBER OF THE JAPANTOWN MERCHANT ASSOCIATION
FOR FOR 40 YEARS FOR DECADES OF DEDICATION TO THE COMMUNITY.
>> HE HELPED ORGANIZE NEARLY EVERY MAJOR CULTURAL EVENT
IN JAPANTOWN INCLUDING THE TEN ABOUT THE FESTIVAL THE OBON
FESTIVAL, THE AKI MATSURI AND THE YEAR END GARRIGA
FESTIVAL. >> AND FITTINGLY HE BROUGHT
COSPLAY TO THE CHERRY BLOSSOM FESTIVAL CREATING THE ANIME
COSTUME CONTEST AND PARADE WHICH BECAME A BELOVED
TRADITION FOR YOUNG FANS AND ARTISTS ALIKE.
HAVING DRESSED UP AS ONE PUNCH MAN ONCE THAT WOULD HAVE BEEN
FUN TO ATTEND AS WELL AS RICH HASHIMOTO OF THE JAPANTOWN
MERCHANT ASSOCIATION REMINDS US MR. AND MRS. PRESENTS MADE THE
NEIGHBORHOOD FEEL ALIVE, JOYFUL AND IN TUNE WITH BOTH TRADITION
AND TRANSFORMATION. >> AND THERE'S SOMETHING POETIC
ABOUT THE WAY MR. NISHI BLENDED THE PAST AND THE FUTURE
HONORING THE DEPTH OF JAPANESE CULTURE WHILE ALSO BRINGING NEW
STORIES INTO THE FOLD. >> HE BELIEVED IN FANDOM BEFORE
IT HAD A NAME. >> HE PRESERVED RITUALS WHILE
CULTIVATING NEW ONES AND HE BUILT A SMALL BUSINESS THAT WAS
IN TRUTH A CULTURAL LIGHTHOUSE. >> EVEN ON JAPAN VIDEO'S FINAL
DAY THIS PAST MAY, HUNDREDS OF FANS RETURNED NOT TO SHOP BUT
TO SAY THANK YOU. TO HONOR THE MAN WHO GAVE THEM
THEIR FIRST GLIMPSE INTO ANOTHER WORLD.
>> SO COLLEAGUES, PLEASE JOIN ME IN RECOGNIZING MR. ONISHI
AND MR. ONISHI FOR GETTING YOUR LAST NAME MR. TAKASHI ONISHI.
>> FOR HIS VISIONARY LEADERSHIP IN INTRODUCING JAPANESE POP
CULTURE TO THE U.S. FOR HIS DECADES OF DEDICATION TO JAPAN
TOWN CIVIC AND CULTURAL LIFE AND FOR THE JOY IMAGINATION
COMMUNITY HE NURTURED THROUGH JAPAN VIDEO AND MEDIA.
MR. ONISHI WE'VE GIVEN GENERATIONS THE GIFT OF WONDER.
AND DOING SO MADE OUR CITY SO PROUD AND ANIMATED.
>> THANK YOU. I HAVE.
THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR. YOU ACTIVELY MENTIONED
EVERYTHING I WANTED TO SAY SO I COME I WANT TO SHOW IT'S HARD
TO BELIEVE IT'S BEEN FOUR YEARS SINCE I OPENED THE STORE
IN 1984 AND TIME WAS FLIES. WE HAD THE WE HAVE MANAGED TO
OVERCOME A DIFFICULTY. RECENTLY WE HAD A PANDEMIC THEN
THE RECESSION AND EVER CHANGING MARKET TREND.
>> I SPONSORED AND THE I INTRODUCED AND PROMOTED
JAPANESE CULTURE TO MAKE THE JAPAN TOWN MORE ATTRACTIVE
AND VIBRANT FOR THE SHOPPERS TO COME TO VISIT.
FOR THAT PURPOSE I ORGANIZED A SERIES OF EVENTS LIKE AS HE
MENTIONED ABOVE I MENTIONED ABOUT THE FESTIVAL OBON DANCE
AND JAPANTOWN ANIME HERE AND THE PROBABLY MY BIGGEST
CONTRIBUTION TO THE COMMUNITY IS IN 1999 I INTRODUCED
AND ORGANIZED ANIME COSTUME PARADE ANIME BEING POPULAR
IN 1997 POKÉMON DRAGON BALL ONE PIECE YOU KNOW WAS VERY POPULAR
AND A LOT THE YOUNGER PEOPLE JUST CONNECTED WITH THE ANIME
COSTUME PARTY RIGHT AWAY ANIME COSTUME PARTY FOR SUPER
CROSSOVER IN A WAY. >> UP UNTIL ABOUT CHERRY
BLOSSOM CHERRY BLOSSOM FESTIVAL WAS MOSTLY TRADITION DOMINATED
FESTIVAL SO SOME DON'T NEED CULTURAL FESTIVAL SO IT'S THE
FIRST TIME I BROUGHT IN CONTEMPORARY CULTURE ANIME
TO THE FESTIVAL WHICH HELP TO DRAW YOUNGER PEOPLE TO THE
FESTIVAL AND HELP TO INCREASE THE PARTICIPATION OF YOUNGER
PEOPLE TO THE FESTIVAL. INCIDENTALLY MY INTRODUCTION OF
ANIME COSTUME PARADE WAS FIRST IN THE UNITED STATES SO I'M
KIND OF PROUD OF YOU. I COULD NOT HAVE DONE THIS SEE
SUPPORTING AND CONTRARY THINK THE COMMUNITY IS MY MISSION SO
I DID. I THINK ALL I CAN DO AND I'M
VERY HAPPY TO RECOGNIZE TODAY MY CONTRIBUTION.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR THANK YOU EVERYBODY
. >> AND NOW DISTRICT EIGHT DARCY
DRAW SINGER COME ON UP. >> HELLO.
IT IS AMAZING WHEN A WHEN A DRAG QUEEN WALKS IN THE ROOM
YOU REALLY YOU KNOW YOU DO NOTICE.
>> YOU NOTICE. COLLEAGUES, IT IS MY GREAT
HONOR TO PRESENT A SPECIAL COMMENDATION ON THE SECOND
TUESDAY OF PRIDE MONTH TO SAN FRANCISCO'S FIRST DRAG LAUREATE
DARCY DOLLINGER. >> DARCY IS A NATIVE SAN
FRANCISCAN ACTOR, WRITER, DIRECTOR, CHOREOGRAPHER,
PRODUCER AND ENTREPRENEUR. IN ADDITION TO BEING THE
COUNTRY'S FIRST EVER DRAG LAUREATE, SAN FRANCISCO'S LGBTQ
PLUS CULTURAL HERITAGE STRATEGY PUBLISHED IN AUGUST OF 2020
PROPOSED THE CREATION OF OR ESTABLISHMENT OF A DRAG
LAUREATE DURING THE DARKEST DAYS OF THE PANDEMIC.
THE HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSION'S LGBTQ LGBTQ I A PLUS ADVISORY
COMMITTEE ADVOCATED FOR IMPLEMENTATION OF THE PROPOSAL
AND IN 2023 MAYOR BREED NAMED DARCY, THE CITY'S FIRST DRAG
LAUREATE JUST IN TIME FOR PRIDE.
>> IT WOULD TURN OUT TO BE AN INSPIRED CHOICE.
DARCY YOU HAVE DONE AN ABSOLUTELY AMAZING JOB AT A
DIFFICULT TIME MANY DIFFICULT TIMES FOR THE CITY.
YOU HAVE BROUGHT UNMITIGATED JOY AND YOU ARE LEAVING BEHIND
A VERY DIFFICULT SET OF HEELS TO FILL.
>> ONE EXAMPLE. THAT SAME YEAR DARCY WORKED
WITH HONEY MAHOGANY FROM THE OFFICE OF TRANSGENDER
INITIATIVES AND WANTING TO MORE TO PRODUCE SAN FRANCISCO IS A
DRAG. A CITYWIDE EVENT THAT HAD 100
DRAG QUEENS AND KINGS OUTPERFORMING ON STREETS ACROSS
SAN FRANCISCO AT THE SAME TIME DARCY IS A FOUNDER OWNER
AND ARTISTIC DIRECTOR OF OASIS WHICH WAS VOTED BEST CABARET
VENUE AND BEST DRAG SHOW BY THE BAY AREA REPORTER IN SUPERVISOR
DORSEY'S DISTRICT AND HE HAS PUT HIMSELF INTO THE QUEUE.
HE WILL BE OFFERING SOME REMARKS ALSO.
>> DARCY AND HER THEN CO-OWNERS OPENED OASIS IN AN 8000 SQUARE
FOOT CONVERTED GAY BATHHOUSE. ON NEW YEAR'S DAY 2015 IN SAN
FRANCISCO'S SOMA DISTRICT HAPPY TEN YEAR ANNIVERSARY YEAR SHE
LAUNCHED OASIS ARTS TO SUPPORT BIPOC AND LGBTQ PLUS ARTISTS BY
PROVIDING MENTORSHIP, VENUE SPACES, EQUIPMENT AND OTHER
RESOURCES TO ELEVATE HISTORICALLY MARGINALIZED
COMMUNITIES. IN THAT VEIN, DURING THE
PANDEMIC, DARCY BROUGHT DRAG TO THE STREETS OF SAN FRANCISCO
THROUGH MEALS ON HEELS, AN INITIATIVE EMPLOYING OUT OF
WORK DRAG ARTISTS WHO BROUGHT FOOD DRINKS AND SOCIALLY
DISTANCED OUTDOOR LIP SYNC PERFORMANCES TO COMMUNITIES
SPREADING JOY AND LIGHT IN HARD TIMES.
NOW OF COURSE FOR SOME DARCY WILL ALWAYS BE KNOWN FOR HER
PORTRAYAL OF BETTY WHITE AS ROSA ISLAND IN THE GOLDEN GIRLS
LIVE. BUT FOR ME MY PERSONAL FAVORITE
DARCY DOLLINGER CREATION IS SEX ETUDE A BODY POSITIVE SEX
POSITIVE DANCE AND FITNESS PROGRAM THAT SHE DESCRIBES AS
MORE THAN A CLASS A COMMUNITY, A MOVEMENT, A DEDICATION TO
BEING MORE AMAZING IN EVERYDAY LIVES.
>> SHORTLY AFTER I WAS ELECTED BACK IN 2018, MY PREDECESSOR
SCOTT WIENER AND I WERE INVITED TO PARTICIPATE IN A DANCE OFF
WHEREIN WE COULD EACH RECRUIT THANK GOD A CREW OF DANCERS TO
REPRESENT US IN A COMPETITION. CAN YOU IMAGINE HOW BAD, HOW
AWFUL THAT WOULD HAVE BEEN? BUT I THINK IT WAS A BOW.
I ASKED DARCY IF I COULD HAVE SEX TO BE MY TEAM AND SHE SAID
YES AND OF COURSE I WON. >> I BELIEVE CLASSES ARE STILL
TAKING PLACE IN DISTRICT EIGHT AT THE ACADEMY OF BALLET ON
SUNDAY MORNINGS. >> DARCY DOLLINGER HAS
DEDICATED HER LIFE TO DAZZLING SAN FRANCISCO WITH POSITIVITY
AND PROVIDING LGBTQ PLUS SAN FRANCISCANS OPPORTUNITIES TO
EXPRESS AND CELEBRATE THEIR FABULOUSNESS.
THROUGH HER WRITING PERFORMANCES, PROGRAMS
AND INITIATIVES, DARCY ELEVATES THE COMMUNITY AND ENSURES THAT
SAN FRANCISCO IS THE VIBRANT AND BEAUTIFUL CITY THAT IT IS.
DARCY DOLLINGER SOON TO BE DRAG LAUREATE EMERITA WE ARE
ETERNALLY GRATEFUL AND I WOULD SAY THE FLOOR IS YOURS BUT IT'S
NOT BECAUSE SUPERVISOR DORSEY WANTS TO SAY SOME THINGS.
>> THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN.
AS ONE OF THE SUPERVISORS WHO ALONG WITH PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN
PROUDLY REPRESENTS SOME OF OUR CITY'S GAYEST AND MOST FABULOUS
NEIGHBORHOODS AND ESTABLISHMENTS, I JUST WANT
TO EXPRESS MY GRATITUDE FIRST TO PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN FOR JUST
A GREAT CHOICE AND A GREAT JOB OF HONORING DARCY BUT SECOND TO
OUR HONORARY DARCY GEORGIA. NOW I SUPPOSE I CAN CLAIM AS A
DISTRICT SIX ICON OASIS, THE LEGENDARY NIGHTCLUB AND CABARET
THAT YOU OWN AND SERVE AS ARTISTIC DIRECTOR OF THIS IS
SOMETHING THIS IS A SPOT THAT MY THEN PARTNER NOW HUSBAND
LOVES FOR THE DRUG DRUNK DRAG AWARDS SHOW FOR THE OSCAR PARTY
. SO WE WILL BE ATTENDING THAT
REGULARLY. BUT AS SAN FRANCISCO'S
INAUGURAL DRAG LAUREATE YOU ARE BIGGER THAN DISTRICT SIX NOW
AND I THINK THIS IS THE GIVEN THE HISTORIC HISTORY MAKING
ROLE, THIS IS SOMETHING THAT IS TO ME YOUR NOW A CITYWIDE STAR
AND A LGBTQ COMMUNITY PIONEER NATIONWIDE AND CONGRATULATIONS
. >> WELL SAID.
A LOT OF THE THINGS I'M GOING TO SAY I'M GONNA SAY A FEW
THINGS. YOU KNOW, I'M VERY HONORED TO
BE HERE SO ALL THE MEMBERS OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS,
FRIENDS AND FAMILY THAT ARE IN THIS ROOM AND ANYONE WHO'S
WATCHING OUT THERE, THANK YOU VERY, VERY MUCH.
>> THIS MEANS THE WORLD TO ME FOR MANY THINGS.
>> BUT AS THE FIRST DRAG LAUREATE OF SAN FRANCISCO
AND OF THE WORLD, THIS IS DEEPLY HUMBLING AND AND REALLY
A POWERFUL MOMENT FOR ME AS MY TWO YEARS SERVING IN THIS
CAPACITY HAVE COME TO AN END. IT'S IT'S NOT LOST ON ME THAT
WE ARE CELEBRATING TODAY SOMETHING THAT IS BIGGER THAN
ME, THAT IS BIGGER THAN MYSELF. WE'RE HONORING THE ART OF DRAG
AND THE STRENGTH OF CULTURE AND THE LEGACY OF A CITY THAT
HAS ALWAYS DARED TO LEAD WITH LOVE, CREATIVITY AND RADICAL
INCLUSION. >> OVER THE PAST YEAR I HAVE
HAD THE JOY OF SHOWING WHAT A DRAG LAUREATE CAN BE THE PAST
TWO YEARS NOT JUST IN WIGS AND SEQUINS BUT IN ACTION.
>> AND I'LL ADMIT THERE HAVE BEEN SOME REALLY AMAZING
PERSONAL EXPERIENCES LIKE GETTING TO THROW THE FIRST
PITCH AT THE GIANTS AT THE GIANTS GAME ACTUALLY.
>> WELL WELL MY FACILITIES OPERATORS HERE MY FACILITIES
MANAGER THERE HE IS. HE HELPED ME LEARN HOW TO
PITCH. I DID PRACTICE.
>> I DID PRACTICE. AND RINGING THE BELL AT THE
WARRIORS GAME, STEPH CURRY WAS PRETTY AMAZING AT CHASE CENTER
AND I'VE BEEN ABLE TO PROGRAM AND HOST THE PRIDE STAGE FOR
BOTH SATURDAY AND SUNDAY. >> LAST YEAR WAS AN EPIC AN
EPIC JOURNEY AND IT WAS VERY REWARDING.
>> AND I EVEN GOT TO MARRY A COUPLE RIGHT HERE IN CITY HALL.
>> THAT WAS PRETTY COOL. >> SAN FRANCISCO HAS LONG BEEN
A BEACON FOR THOSE WHO DARE TO LIVE, LOVE AND EXPRESS
THEMSELVES FREELY AND I'VE HAD THE PRIVILEGE OF REPRESENTING
DRAG AND OUR COMMUNITY ON SOME OF THE BIGGEST PLATFORM IN THE
CITY. >> BUT I'VE DONE SO KNOWING
THAT I'M STANDING ON THE SHOULDERS OF GIANTS OF QUEENS
AND KINGS AND PERFORMERS AND ARTISTS WHO HAVE PAVED THE
WAY MANY OF WHOM NEVER GOT THE SPOTLIGHT THEY DESERVE.
SO TODAY I ALSO WANT TO HONOR THEM FROM THE COMPTON CAFETERIA
RIOT TO THE SISTERS OF PERPETUAL INDULGENCE OUR
HISTORY IS WRITTEN IN BOLD EYELINER AND EVEN BOLDER
ACTIONS. IT'S IN THE FEATHER BOAS, THE
PROTESTS, THE LAUGHTER, THE MORNING AND THE UNYIELDING
CREATIVITY THAT DRAG EMBODIES. I ALSO WANT TO BE CLEAR THAT
NONE OF THIS HAPPENS ALONE. I AM SURROUNDED BY AN
EXTRAORDINARY TEAM OF PEOPLE WHO SHOW UP WITH BRILLIANCE
AND PASSION EVERY SINGLE DAY. >> TO EVERYONE WHO WORKS WITH
ME AND FOR ME AND INHABITS MY ORBIT, THIS COMMENDATION ALSO
BELONGS TO YOU. >> I'M ONLY AS STRONG AS THE
COMMUNITY THAT LIFTS ME UP. I AM NOT ONLY THE DRAG LAUREATE
BUT AS YOU SAID I'M A SMALL BUSINESS OWNER AND THE
EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF AN ARTS NONPROFIT A PLAYWRIGHT, A
FILMMAKER, A DANCE TEACHER AND A SAN FRANCISCO NATIVE
AND OVER THE PAST TWO YEARS I'M VERY PROUD OF MY ORGANIZATIONS
. COLLECTIVELY WE'VE BEEN ABLE TO
PAY UPWARDS OF $1.6 MILLION TO PERFORMERS, ARTISTS
AND DESIGNERS. >> THAT IS NOT JUST A NUMBER.
IT IS LIVELIHOODS. IT IS RENT, IT IS HEALTH CARE.
IT IS DIGNITY. IT'S A COMMITMENT TO BUILDING A
SUSTAINABLE FUTURE FOR ART AND ARTISTRY IN THE BAY AREA.
>> BEING DRAG LAUREATE IS ALSO ABOUT MORE THAN CELEBRATION.
IT'S ABOUT RESPONSIBILITY. IT'S ABOUT USING THIS PLATFORM
TO CREATE OPPORTUNITY AMPLIFY VOICES AND CHALLENGE SYSTEMS
THAT ATTEMPT TO DIM OUR LIGHT. >> SO TO THE CITY OF SAN
FRANCISCO, THANK YOU FOR RECOGNIZING THE POWER AND THE
PURPOSE OF DRAG. >> THANK YOU FOR GIVING THIS
ART FORM THE OFFICIAL SPACE THAT IT HAS ALWAYS DESERVED.
AND TO EVERY YOUNG PERSON OUT THERE WONDERING IF THERE'S ROOM
IN THE WORLD FOR YOUR MAGIC. LET THIS BE YOUR SIGN THAT YES
THERE IS. >> YOU KNOW, IT MAY FEEL
PARTICULARLY SCARY RIGHT NOW WHEN OUR FEDERAL GOVERNMENT IS
LITERALLY OUT TO ERASE US. >> BUT OUR POWER THE REAL POWER
IS THE POWER WE HAVE TOGETHER. AND IT IS THE POWER OF A
STRONG, UNSHAKABLE COMMUNITY. >> SO I FOR ONE AND I INVITE
ALL OF US TO KEEP PUSHING TO KEEP SHINING, TO KEEP STRIDING
AND MARCHING FORWARD IN HEELS AND LOVE AND IN UNITY.
>> THANK YOU FROM THE BOTTOM OF MY VERY FULL AND GLITTER
ENCRUSTED HEART. THANK YOU, DARCY.
>> BETWEEN US AND YOU ALL AND MAKE ANYBODY WANT TO COME
UP COME UP HERE. OH, YEAH, YEAH.
COME ON UP HERE. OKAY.
>> EVERYONE ELSE IS GOING TO COME TODAY.
OH, YOU. I DON'T KNOW.
>> I REALLY LOVE HER. >> TWO 30 SPECIAL
COMMENDATIONS. WE HAD SOME GREAT, GREAT PEOPLE
TODAY. >> ALL RIGHT, SO WE WILL NOW
TRY TO RECOVER SOME OF OUR TIME .
MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE CALL ITEM 16?
>> ITEM 16. THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO
AUTHORIZE THE DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS AND SUPPORT OF
HOUSING TO RETROACTIVELY ACCEPT AND EXPEND AN APPROXIMATE $8
MILLION. THIS IS A GRANT IN PROPOSITION
47 GRANT PROGRAM FUNDS COHORT FOUR FOR A PROGRAM ENTITLED
HOUSING AND EXPUNGEMENT AND RECOVERY THROUGH TREATMENT
AND SUPPORTIVE SERVICES OR HEARTS.
FOR COSTS INCURRED BEGINNING OCTOBER THIRD, 2024 THROUGH
JUNE 30TH 2028. AND TO AUTHORIZE THE EXECUTION
OF A GRANT AGREEMENT WITH THE CALIFORNIA BOARD OF STATE
AND COMMUNITY CORRECTIONS. >> ALL RIGHT.
I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL THIS WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE CALL ITEM 17?
>> ITEM 17. THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO
AUTHORIZE THE DIRECTOR OF THE MUNICIPAL TRANSPORTATION AGENCY
TO EXECUTE CONTRACT NUMBER AS TWO DASH 2025 DASH 28 DASH LLC
PHASE ONE RV FOR BRAKE SYSTEM OVERHAUL WITH WABTEC PASSENGER
TRANSIT TO PERFORM THE SCHEDULED OVERHAUL OF KEY
COMPONENTS OF THE LR V FOR BRAKE SYSTEM ON 68 VEHICLES FOR
A CONTRACT AMOUNT OF APPROXIMATELY 15.5 MILLION
AND A TWO YEAR AND SIX MONTH TERM AND WE'LL TAKE THIS SAME
HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS
ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL
ITEMS 18 THROUGH 21 TOGETHER ITEMS 18 THROUGH 21 OR FOR
RESOLUTION THAT RETROACTIVELY AUTHORIZE ACCEPTING
AND EXPENDING GIFTS AND GRANTS FOR THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC
HEALTH. ITEM 18 IS FOR $265,000 A GRANT
FROM THE CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH CARE SERVICES FOR THE
BLUE CROSS OF CALIFORNIA PARTNERSHIP PLAN INC TO
PARTICIPATE IN A PROGRAM CALIFORNIA ADVANCING
AND INNOVATING MEDICAL CAPACITY BUILDING INCENTIVE PAYMENT
PROGRAM THROUGH JUNE 30TH, 2025.
ITEM 19 IS FOR A MONETARY GIFT OF 37,500 FROM THE EPIC SYSTEMS
CORPORATION TO SUPPORT THE COMMUNITY RESOURCE DIRECTORY
AND BEHAVIORAL HEALTH PROJECT THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2025.
ITEM 20 IS FOR A MONETARY GIFT ENTITLED RAMS RICHMOND AREA
MULTI SERVICES FOR 37,000 FROM THE EPIC SYSTEMS CORPORATION TO
HELP LOW INCOME AND AT RISK POPULATIONS FOR THE TERM
THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2024 AND ITEM 21 THIS IS FOR A GIFT VALUED
IN THE AMOUNT OF 1.74 MILLION FROM THE SAN FRANCISCO PUBLIC
HEALTH FOUNDATION IN SUPPORT OF VARIOUS PUBLIC HEALTH
PROGRAMMATIC NEEDS THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2025.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM 22. ITEM 22 RESOLUTION TO APPROVE
FOR PURPOSES OF SECTION 147 F OF THE INTERNAL REVENUE CODE OF
1986 AS AMENDED THE ISSUANCE OF TAX EXEMPT OBLIGATIONS PURSUANT
TO A PLAN OF FINANCE BY CALIFORNIA STATEWIDE
COMMUNITIES DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY IN AN AMOUNT OF 165
MILLION ISSUED BY THE SEQUOIA SAN FRANCISCO FOR THE PURPOSE
OF FINANCING REIMBURSING ACQUISITION, CONSTRUCTION,
RENOVATION, EQUIPPING AND FURNISHING OF A SENIOR
RESIDENTIAL AND CARE SERVICES AND CERTAIN OTHER MATTERS
RELATING THERE TO AND AGAIN SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 23.
ITEM 23 ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE PLANNING CODE TO ELIMINATE
RETAIL USE SIZE LIMITS ON HEALTH SERVICES USES
AND REPRODUCTIVE HEALTH CLINICS IN THE MUOH THE MIXED USE
OFFICE DISTRICT EAST OF SEVENTH STREET TO ELIMINATE RETAIL
RATIO LIMITS IN THE MUO DISTRICT EAST OF SEVENTH
STREET. AND TO AFFIRM THE SECOND
DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS
24 AND 25 TOGETHER ITEMS 24 AND 25 ARE TWO MOTIONS THAT
APPROVE THE MAYOR'S NOMINATION FOR REAPPOINTMENT TO THE
HISTORIC PRESERVATION COMMISSION.
TERMS ENDING DECEMBER 31ST 2028 FOR ITEM 24 CHRIS FOLEY 425
DIANE MATSUDA. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTIONS ARE ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 26 ITEM 26 THIS IS A MOTION TO
APPROVE THE MAYOR'S NOMINATION FOR THE APPOINTMENT OF STUART
PARMENTER TO THE SANITATION AND STREETS COMMISSION TERM
ENDING JULY 1ST, 2028. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS APPROVED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 27 ITEM 27 AS A MOTION TO
APPOINT BRUCE WOLF TO THE SUNSHINE ORDINANCE TASK FORCE
TERM ENDING APRIL 27TH 2027. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS APPROVED.
MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO COMMITTEE REPORTS PLEASE CALL
ITEM 28 YES. >> THE FOLLOWING ITEMS WILL BE
CONSIDERED BY THE GOVERNMENT. WE'RE CONSIDERED EXCUSE ME BY
THE GOVERNMENT AUDIT AND OVERSIGHT COMMITTEE AT A
REGULAR MEETING ON THURSDAY JUNE 5TH AND WERE RECOMMENDED
AS COMMITTEE REPORTS. ITEM 28 WAS RECOMMENDED AS
AMENDED WITH THE SAME TITLE IT READS ORDINANCE TO FIX
COMPENSATION FOR PERSONS EMPLOYED BY THE CITY AND COUNTY
WHOSE COMPENSATION IS SUBJECT TO THE PROVISIONS OF CHARTER
SECTION 8.409 IN JOB CODES NOT REPRESENTED BY AN EMPLOYEE
ORGANIZATION AND TO ESTABLISH WORKING SCHEDULES AND OTHER
TERMS AND CONDITIONS OF EMPLOYMENT AND METHODS OF
PAYMENT EFFECTIVE JULY FIRST 2025.
>> SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS
PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 29.
>> ITEM 29 WAS RECOMMENDED AS A COMMITTEE REPORT.
IT'S AN ORDINANCE TO ADOPT AND IMPLEMENT THE SECOND
AMENDMENT TO THE 2024 THROUGH 2027 MEMORANDUM OF
UNDERSTANDING BETWEEN THE CITY AND COUNTY AND THE SERVICE
EMPLOYEES INTERNATIONAL UNION LOCAL 1021 STAFF AND PER DIEM
NURSES TO ADDRESS THE ORDER OF SELECTION FOR FILLING VACANT
NURSING POSITIONS. >> SAME HOUSE SAME CALL THE
ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL
ITEMS 30 AND 31 TOGETHER ITEMS 30 AND 31 OR 2 RESOLUTIONS THAT
AUTHORIZE THE MAYOR OR HIS DESIGNEE TO CAST ASSESSMENT
BALLOTS IN THE AFFIRMATIVE FOR THE PROPOSED RENEWAL
AND EXPANSION FOR TWO PROPERTY AND BUSINESS IMPROVEMENT
DISTRICTS WITH RESPECT TO CERTAIN PARCELS OF REAL
PROPERTY OWNED BY THE CITY SUBJECT TO ASSESSMENT IN THE
FOLLOWING DISTRICTS FOR ITEM 30 IT'S KNOWN AS THE OCEAN AVENUE
COMMUNITY BENEFIT DISTRICT. ITEM 31 WAS RECOMMENDED AS
AMENDED WITH THE SAME TITLE IT IS KNOWN AS THE DOGPATCH
AND NORTHWEST POTRERO HILL GREEN BENEFIT DISTRICT
AND AGAIN SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION ARE ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
32. ITEM 32 WAS RECOMMENDED AS A
COMMITTEE REPORT. IT'S A RESOLUTION TO AUTHORIZE
THE MAYOR MEMBERS OF THE MAYOR'S OFFICE AND THE DIRECTOR
OF THE OFFICE OF ECONOMIC AND WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT TO
SOLICIT DONATIONS FROM NONPROFITS, PRIVATE
ORGANIZATIONS, GRANT MAKERS, FOUNDATIONS AND OTHER PERSONS
AND ENTITIES FOR THE PURPOSE OF SUPPORTING THE CONTINUED
ECONOMIC REVITALIZATION OF SAN FRANCISCO FOR SIX MONTHS FROM
THE EFFECTIVE DATE OF THIS RESOLUTION NOTWITHSTANDING THE
BEHEST OF PAYMENT ORDINANCE. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 30 THREE.
ITEM 33 WAS RECOMMENDED AS A COMMITTEE REPORT.
IT'S A MOTION TO DIRECT THE BUDGET AND LEGISLATIVE ANALYST
TO INITIATE A PERFORMANCE AUDIT IN FISCAL YEAR 2025 THROUGH 26
OF THE RECREATION AND PARK DEPARTMENT.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS A OR THE MOTION IS APPROVED.
>> MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO A ROLL CALL FIRST MEMBER UP TO
INTRODUCE NEW BUSINESS IS SUPERVISOR MELGAR.
>> SUBMIT THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR SARTOR SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHERYL SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU,
MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES TODAY I'M
INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION IN SUPPORT OF AB 1242 AUTHORED
BY ASSEMBLY MEMBER STEPHANIE WYNN.
AB 1242 STRENGTHENS CALIFORNIA'S LANGUAGE ACCESS
LAWS TO ENSURE THAT PEOPLE WITH LIMITED ENGLISH PROFICIENCY
AND THOSE WHO ARE DEAF OR HARD OF HEARING CAN EQUITABLY ACCESS
GOVERNMENT SERVICES. THE BILL EXPANDS THE DEFINITION
OF WHO IS CONSIDERED A SUBSTANTIAL LANGUAGE GROUP TO
INCLUDE THOSE ELIGIBLE FOR SERVICES NOT JUST THOSE ALREADY
SERVED HELPING CLOSE ACCESS GAPS PROACTIVE LEE IT
MODERNIZING OUTDATED SURVEYS BY REQUIRING COMPREHENSIVE DATA
DRIVEN ASSESSMENTS USING UC CENSUS DATA AND COMMUNITY
INPUT. AB 1242 ALSO ESTABLISHES A
LANGUAGE ACCESS DIRECTOR WITHIN THE HEALTH AND HUMAN SERVICES
AGENCY TO COORDINATE IMPLEMENTATION ACROSS
DEPARTMENTS EACH OF WHICH MUST DEVELOP A LANGUAGE ACCESS PLAN
WITH STATE OVERSIGHT AND FUNDING.
THIS BILL ALIGNS CLOSELY WITH SAN FRANCISCO'S LONGSTANDING
COMMITMENT TO LANGUAGE ACCESS EQUITY AND CULTURALLY COMPETENT
DELIVERY OF PUBLIC SERVICES FOR DIVERSE COMMUNITIES.
THE REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WALTON. SUPERVISOR CHIN THANK YOU,
MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES TODAY I WOULD LIKE
TO CLOSE TODAY'S MEETING IN MEMORY OF SHAWN O'NEAL
MCGREW WHO PASSED AWAY ON FRIDAY, FEBRUARY 28TH OF THIS
YEAR. BEFORE HE RETIRED IN 2023 AS A
GENERAL MANAGER OF THE MILL VALLEY RECREATION DEPARTMENT,
SHAWN CONTRIBUTED OVER 26 YEARS OF HIS CAREER HERE AT THE SAN
FRANCISCO RECREATION AND PARK DEPARTMENT WHERE HE SERVED AS
THE RECREATION DIRECTOR WHO CREATED THE FIRST SURFING CAMP
SUPERVISOR FOR FOUR LATCHKEY AND AQUATIC PROGRAMS
AND COMMUNITY SERVICE SUPERVISOR AT THE RICHMOND
RECREATION CENTER. SHAWN WAS A FOURTH GENERATION
BORN AND RAISED IN SAN FRANCISCO AND HE WENT TO GEORGE
WASHINGTON HIGH SCHOOL AND LATER GRADUATED FROM UC
SANTA BARBARA. HIS PASSION FOR RECREATION
AND ARTS STARTED IN HIS TEENAGE YEARS WHERE HE USED TO SPEND
HIS SUMMER BREAKS WORKING AS A YOUTH WORKER AT MANY OF OUR
PUBLIC SWIMMING POOLS INCLUDING ONE SUMMER AT LAKE MORISSET.
HIS FAVORITE POOL REMAINED TO BE THE MISSION COMMUNITY POOL
AS REALLY THE ONLY OUTDOOR POOL IN SAN FRANCISCO PUBLIC OUTDOOR
POOL IN SAN FRANCISCO AND MANY LOCALS CALLED IT NICKEL POOL
BECAUSE OF THE HISTORIC ENTRANCE FEE OF ONLY A NICKEL.
SEAN TOUCH MANY PEOPLE MYSELF INCLUDED WITH HIS AMAZING
ENERGY AND THROUGH HIS FRIENDSHIPS, TRAVEL AND CAREER
. MY DEEPEST CONDOLENCES TO HIS
MOM SHAUNA WHO WAS HERE TODAY IN THE AUDIENCE.
WE ENTIRE BOARD SUPERVISOR AND REALLY THE CITY WE SEND OUR
LOVE TO YOU. THANK YOU FOR BEING HERE
AND SHAWN WILL BE GREATLY MISSED NOT JUST FOR WHO HE WAS
TO ALL OF US JUST ALL HIS LOVE AND CARE FOR OUR COMMUNITY.
WE ARE JUST SO GRATEFUL. I AM JUST SO GRATEFUL TO HAVE
KNOWN SHAWN AND SO AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR CHAN. SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU,
MADAM CLERK. >> COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM
INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION CONDEMNING THE ADOPTION
ABDUCTIONS OF IMMIGRANTS BY THE IMMIGRATIONS AND CUSTOMS
ENFORCEMENT ICE AGENCY. >> THIS RESOLUTION IT'S
IN RESPONSE TO THE DEVASTATING AND WIDESPREAD REMOVAL OF
IMMIGRANTS INCLUDING THOSE WITH NO CRIMINAL RECORD WHO ARE
DILIGENTLY COOPERATING WITH LAW ENFORCEMENT.
>> LAST WEEK ICE USE MILITARY STYLE OPERATION TO SEIZE PEOPLE
GOING TO WORK SCHOOL GRADUATIONS AND IMMIGRATION
COURT IN SAN FRANCISCO AND LOS ANGELES.
MANY DO NOT HAVE CRIMINAL RECORDS INCLUDING A CHILD AS
YOUNG AS THREE YEARS OLD. >> YOUTH WITH BRIGHT FUTURES
AHEAD HOW WORKING PARENTS AND SEIU CALIFORNIA UNION
PRESIDENT DAVID HERRERA. THEY ARE OUR NEIGHBORS, OUR
FRIENDS, OUR COWORKERS, OUR FATHERS AND MOTHERS.
>> GRANDPARENTS AND CHILDREN. THIS INDIVIDUALS VERSUS THEY
WOULD DECLARE ID OR EXPLANATION OF CHARGES BEING DETAINED
WITHOUT IMMEDIATE ACCESS TO LEGAL COUNSEL.
>> ALL FAMILY NOTIFICATION. WE ARE SEEING ASSERTIVE FORCE
AND AND INTIMIDATION DURING ARRESTS.
>> THIS REMOVALS HAVE A CHILLING EFFECT ON THE REST OF
OUR CITY TO US OUT OF WORKING PEOPLE IMMIGRANT COMMUNITIES
AND SMALL BUSINESS IMPACTED. >> THIS JUST DISRUPTS OUR WORK
FORCE. >> DESTABILIZE OUR ECONOMY
UNDERMINES PUBLIC TRUST IN LAW ENFORCEMENT AND INCITES FEAR SO
EVERYDAY PEOPLE WILL BE TOO SCARED TO ACCESS PROPER
SERVICES. >> I HOPE THIS BOARD CAN STAND
TOGETHER IN CALLING FOR AN IMMEDIATE CESSATION OF THIS
BRUTAL BRUTAL OF THIS BRUTAL PRACTICES AND URGING ICE TO
ADHERE STRICTLY TO DUE PROCESS THE UNIVERSAL RIGHTS TO FAMILY
UNITY, THE HUMANE TREATMENT OF MIGRANT COMMUNITIES WHO SAFELY
AND LAWFULLY PURSUE THEIR CLAIMS.
>> I WANT TO THANK MY COLLEAGUES SUPERVISOR WALTON
MOORE MALKIA MENTOR SALTER AND FIELDER FOR THEIR EARLY
CO-SPONSORSHIP. I LOOK FORWARD TO MY OTHER
COLLEAGUES COAST COLLEAGUES, CO-SPONSORSHIP AND VOTE.
>> MADAM CLARA I ALSO HAVE A MEMORIAL.
COLLEAGUES I WOULD LIKE TO ADJOURN TODAY'S MEETING
IN MEMORY OF LOUISA POOLE. SHE WAS A FEARLESS LEADER
FIGHTER? >> SISTER AND BRIGHT LIGHT
IN THE ASIAN AMERICAN LABOR MOVEMENT.
>> AS A UNION LEADER SHE FOUGHT .
>> SHE FOUGHT FOR FAIRNESS AND JUSTICE.
>> DURING HER 50 YEAR CAREER SHE MAKES SURE ALL WORKING
PEOPLE ESPECIALLY THOSE IN HEALTH CARE AND PUBLIC
SERVICES WERE TREATED WITH DIGNITY AND RESPECT.
>> SHE MADE HISTORY AS THE FIRST AMERICAN TO BE ELECTED TO
SERVE AS THE EXECUTIVE VICE PRESIDENT OF SEIU, ONE OF THE
LARGEST UNIONS IN THE COUNTRY. >> IN 1977 LOUISA STARTED
WORKING AS A NURSE AT SAN FRANCISCO GENERAL HOSPITAL.
>> AT A TIME WHEN PEOPLE WITH AIDS WERE OFTEN IGNORED
AND THERE LOUISA STOOD UP AND SAID THEY DESERVE CARE
AND COMPASSION SHOULD PUSH PUBLIC HEALTH OFFICIALS TO MAKE
SURE FRONTLINE WORKERS HAD THE TRAINING AND SUPPORT THEY
NEEDED. THAT WAS JUST THE BEGINNING OF
HER LIFETIME OF STANDING UP FOR LEADERS FOR OTHERS.
>> SHE WENT ON TO CO-FOUND SEIU NURSE ALLIANCE ORGANIZED HEALTH
CARE WORKERS IN LAS VEGAS AND THE TSA WORKERS AT SAN
FRANCISCO AIRPORT. SHE BELIEVED EVERYONE DESERVED
TO BE HEARD AND SHE WORKED HARD TO MAKE THAT HAPPEN.
>> LOUISA WAS A STRONG VOICE IN THE FILIPINO COMMUNITY A
MENTOR TO MANY ORGANIZERS. >> SHE ALWAYS LEFT WITH
KINDNESS AND STRENGTH WHEREAS SHE WAS ON THE PICKET LINE IN A
MEETING OR MENTORING YOUNG LEADERS.
>> LOUISA IS ONE OF THE HIGHEST RANKING AAPI LEADERS IN THE
LABOR IN THE LABOR MOVEMENT AND I HAD THE PRIVILEGE OF
WORKING ALONGSIDE HER WITH HER SINCE 2008.
TOGETHER WE HAVE FOUGHT FOR HEALTH CARE WORKERS ACROSS
CALIFORNIA NAVIGATING CITY COUNTY, STATE AND FEDERAL
BUDGETS, NEGOTIATING CONTRACTS AT INDIVIDUAL HEALTH CARE
FACILITIES AND EVEN ORGANIZED INTERNATIONALLY IN THE
PHILIPPINES, INDIA, CAMBODIA AND CHINA.
>> LOUISA EYE HAS SHOWN ME WHAT IS POSSIBLE WHEN COURAGE,
CONVICTIONS AND COMPASSION ALL COME TOGETHER.
>> LOUISA HAS JOINED THE ANCESTORS BY HER SPIRIT.
>> IT'S WHAT AS ALWAYS. HER LEGACY LIVES ON THE PEOPLE
WHO STAND TALL BECAUSE OF HER. >> AND YOUNG LEADERS SHOULD
PAVE THE WAY FOR AND IN COUNTLESS FIGHT FOR JUSTICE AS
SHE CHAMPIONED. >> REST IN POWER.
DO WE SUPPORT THE RESSA SUMMIT ?
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHEN.
MADAM CLERK, CAN WE DO THAT FOR THE FULL BOARD?
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. >> SUPERVISOR DORSEY SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR AND GUARDIAN SUBMIT
. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MY MY COLLEAGUES TODAY WE ARE WITNESSING HISTORY
UNFOLD BEFORE OUR EYES. >> LAST WEEK ON JUNE FIFTH,
2025 AT LEAST 15 PEOPLE INCLUDING A THREE YEAR OLD
CHILD WERE DETAINED BY FEDERAL IMMIGRATION AGENTS AT A SAN
FRANCISCO ICE FIELD OFFICE DURING WHAT ADVOCATES DESCRIBED
AS A ROUTINE CHECK IN. >> THIS MORNING WE HEARD OF
ADDITIONAL INCIDENTS WHERE THE ICE FACILITY HAD TO BE SHUT
DOWN DUE TO AGAIN UNJUST INTERVENTION BY THE FEDERAL
ADMINISTRATION. >> LET'S BE CLEAR ABOUT WHAT IS
HAPPENING. THESE WERE PEOPLE WHO WERE
ATTEMPTING TO FOLLOW OUR LEGAL PROCESS, ABIDE BY THE LAW
AND WERE INSTEAD MET WITH WHAT THEY FEARED MOST WOULD HAPPEN.
>> THIS TACTIC FROM ICE TRAUMATIZES FAMILIES AND ERODES
TRUST IN PUBLIC INSTITUTIONS AND IS INTENDED TO SERVE
AND PROTECT OUR RESIDENTS. >> IT MAKES OUR COMMUNITIES
LESS SAFE. IT STOKES THE FLAMES OF FEAR
FOR OUR MOST VULNERABLE. >> IT'S WHY I WAS HONORED TO
CO-SPONSOR SUPERVISOR CHEN'S LEGISLATION AS WELL IN OUR
SISTER CITY OF L.A. THOUGH WE'VE SEEN LABOR LEADERS LIKE
DAVID WORK TO DETAIN FOR EXERCISING THEIR FIRST
AMENDMENT RIGHT. THE NATIONAL GUARD AND MARINES
HAVE BEEN DEPLOYED. THE ARMED FORCES HAVE BEEN
DEPLOYED AGAINST OUR OWN PEOPLE TO INTIMIDATE US AND DIVIDE US
. >> THIS IS A FUNDAMENTAL
VIOLATION OF OUR CIVIL RIGHTS. PROTESTERS ACROSS CALIFORNIA
AND IN SAN FRANCISCO HAVE MOBILIZED IN RESPONSE CALLING
FOR THE PROTECTION OF IMMIGRANTS, THE
DEMILITARIZATION OF CIVIC LIFE AND THE UPHOLDING OF
FUNDAMENTAL DEMOCRATIC RIGHTS. >> IN DOING SO, REPORTS HAVE
SURFACED OF JOURNALISTS BOTH IN LOS ANGELES AND SAN
FRANCISCO JOURNALISTS BEING THREATENED, HARASSED OR INJURED
WHILE COVERING RECENT PRO-FASCIST PROTESTS IN SAN
FRANCISCO. >> THE REPORTS WERE OF STUDENT
JOURNALISTS. THIS IS A THREAT TO THE FREEDOM
OF PRESS, TO THE PEOPLE, SAFEGUARD OF TRANSPARENCY AND A
KEY TOOL TO HOLDING POWER ACCOUNTABLE WHICH SHOULD
OPERATE WITH GUARANTEED FREEDOM TO REPORT WITHOUT GOVERNMENT
INTERFERENCE OR RETALIATION. >> ALL OF US SITTING IN THESE
CHANGER CHAMBERS SWORE AN OATH OF OFFICE TO PROTECT AND DEFEND
THE CONSTITUTION FROM ALL ENEMIES FOREIGN AND DOMESTIC.
>> WE DON'T HAVE TO WAIT FOR THE HISTORY BOOKS TO JUDGE US.
THERE HAS NEVER BEEN MORE CLARITY ABOUT WHAT IS RIGHT.
>> OUR CITY HAS ALWAYS BEEN A BEACON OF HOPE, HAS ALWAYS LED
THE WAY ON WHAT IS RIGHT. AND COLLEAGUES, I HOPE WE SHOW
OUR RESIDENTS THAT THERE IS NO CHANCE OF THAT STOPPING ANYTIME
SOON. >> AT A TIME WHEN MANY OF OUR
CONSTITUENTS ARE LIVING IN FEAR, IT IS OUR
RESPONSIBILITY AS ELECTED OFFICIALS TO ACT BRAVELY
AND FIGHT FOR THE FUNDAMENTAL RIGHTS OF OUR RESIDENTS.
BECAUSE DESPITE WHAT THE PRESIDENT MAY SAY, THAT IS WHAT
IT MEANS TO BE AN AMERICAN. TO OUR RESIDENTS OUR HOPE MUST
BE STRONGER THAN OUR FEAR. AND YOU HAVE MY COMMITMENT THAT
THIS BODY WILL FIGHT FOR OUR DEMOCRACY AND WE WILL FIGHT FOR
YOU. >> SO I'M INTRODUCING A
RESOLUTION TODAY AFFIRMING THE PUBLIC'S RIGHT TO PEACEFULLY
ASSEMBLE AND PROTEST ACTIONS OF THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT
CONDEMNING THE MILITARIZATION OF CIVILIAN RESPONSE TO
PEACEFUL PROTESTS AND REAFFIRMING SAN SAN
FRANCISCO'S COMMITMENT TO IMMIGRANT JUSTICE AND THE
CITY'S SANCTUARY ORDINANCE. >> I KNOW SUPERVISOR FIELDER
COULDN'T BE HERE TODAY BUT I'D LIKE TO RECOGNIZE HER FOR HER
CONTINUED ADVOCACY AND PARTNERSHIP ON THIS
LEGISLATION. I'D LIKE TO THANK SUPERVISOR
FIELDER CHEN WALTON AND MELGAR FOR YOUR EARLY SUPPORT FOR THIS
RESOLUTION AS CO-SPONSORS AS WELL.
>> AND LASTLY, I WOULD LIKE TO THANK SAM LOGAN IN MY OFFICE
FOR WORKING ON THIS RESOLUTION IN REAL TIME AND ADAPTING TO
THE CHANGING CONDITIONS THAT WE'RE SEEING NEARLY EVERY HOUR
OVER THE LAST 24 TO 48 HOURS AS WELL.
THANK YOU ALL AND COLLEAGUES AND I HOPE YOU'LL JOIN US
IN SUPPORTING THIS AS WELL. >> THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR OBAMA
. NEXT I'D LIKE TO HAVE MY SECOND
INTRODUCTION. >> COLLEAGUES, WE ARE ELECTED
TO SERVE OUR RESIDENTS AND TO MAKE SURE THEY FEEL SAFE BUT TO
ALSO LISTEN TO THEM AND IMPROVE THEIR QUALITY OF LIFE.
>> WE CAN CALL OUT THE INJUSTICE AT OUR DOORSTEP
AND TAKE CARE OF BUSINESS HERE AT HOME.
>> SO TODAY I WILL BE INTRODUCING TWO LETTERS OF
INQUIRY REGARDING THE 311 MOBILE APP.
>> TWO WEEKS AGO THE CHRONICLE REPORTED THAT WHILE HOMELESS
ENCAMPMENTS HAVE REACHED A FIVE YEAR LOW, REPORTS OF
ENCAMPMENTS ON THE 31 APP ARE INCREASING.
SO WHICH BEGS THE QUESTION WHAT IS CAUSING THIS DISCREPANCY?
>> THE ISSUE LIES IN HOW 311 REPORTS ARE CATEGORIZED.
RESIDENTS DON'T HAVE OPTIONS TO REPORT ISSUES LIKE
NON-EMERGENCY DRUG ACTIVITY, OPEN AIR DRUG USE, PUBLIC
INTOXICATION, DRUG USE WITHIN ENCAMPMENTS DIRECTLY SO THEY
OFTEN JUST CHOOSE ENCAMPMENT AS THE CLOSEST MATCH.
>> THIS LEADS TO MISLEADING DATA AND WHEN CITY DEPARTMENTS
RELY ON BAD DATA THEY CAN'T DEPLOY THE RIGHT RESOURCES TO
HELP THOSE RESIDENTS IN NEED. THE THREE WOMAN SYSTEM REMAINS
ONE OF THE MOST DIRECT AND VITAL TOOL RESIDENTS USE TO
ENGAGE WITH OUR GOVERNMENT AND PARTICIPATE IN SAN
FRANCISCO AS ACTIVELY ENGAGED CITIZENS.
UNDERSTANDING HOW THIS PLATFORM IS EVOLVING ESPECIALLY TO
INCREASE USABILITY RESPONSIVENESS AND COORDINATED
INTEGRATION WITH CITY AGENCIES. IT IS ESSENTIAL TO ENSURE IT
MEETS THE NEEDS OF ALL COMMUNITIES.
>> THE PURPOSE OF THESE LETTERS IS TWOFOLD.
THE FIRST WILL INQUIRE FROM THE CITY ADMINISTRATOR'S OFFICE
AND THE DEPARTMENT OF EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT ABOUT PLANNED
IMPROVEMENTS OR ENHANCEMENT ENHANCEMENTS TO SAN FRANCISCO'S
311 SYSTEM PARTICULARLY THE 311 MOBILE APP WHICH IS OF
PARTICULAR INTEREST GIVEN THE LAST PSA VIDEO CREATED ON HOW
TO USE THE APP CAME OUT 11 YEARS AGO.
>> THE SECOND WILL REQUEST THAT THE CITY ADMINISTRATOR'S
OFFICE, DEPARTMENT OF EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT AND SAN FRANCISCO
POLICE DEPARTMENT SHARE HOW WE CAN IMPROVE DATA ACCURACY TO
BETTER RESPOND TO CASES AND IMPROVE OUR UNDERSTANDING
OF SAFETY AND STREET CONDITIONS.
I LOOK FORWARD TO THE RESPONSES FROM THESE RESPECTIVE
DEPARTMENTS. >> THE REST I SUBMIT THANK YOU
. >> SUPERVISOR SUPERVISOR
MIDDLEMAN. >> I WILL SUBMIT MY
LEGISLATION. THANK YOU MR. PRESIDENT.
AND SEEING NO NAMES ON THE ROSTER THAT CONCLUDES THE
INTRODUCTION OF NEW BUSINESS. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
LET'S GO TO PUBLIC COMMENT. AT THIS TIME THE BOARD WELCOMES
YOUR GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT. >> YOU CAN LINE UP ON YOUR
RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER ALONG THE CURTAINS.
YOU MAY SPEAK TO THE MAYOR ON APPEARANCE.
YOU MAY SPEAK TO THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED.
>> TWO ITEMS 36 AND 37 AND OTHER GENERAL MATTERS NOT
ON THE AGENDA BUT MUST BE WITHIN THE BOARD SUBJECT MATTER
JURISDICTION. WE ARE SETTING THE TIMER FOR
TWO MINUTES. LET'S WELCOME OUR FIRST
SPEAKER. >> WELCOME.
WELCOME BACK. >> WHAT I'VE JUST HEARD IT
MEANS THAT YES, THE RAILROAD IS SHOWN IS ON A IS EXCELLENT.
ANYWHERE NOBODY ONE CAN STOP IT.
WE'RE GOING TO MEASURE THE EYES.
OF COURSE THE WALL CLEAR WATER ON THE POISON OAK.
YOU JUST PAY ATTENTION. YOU HAVE TWO MINUTES.
YOU JUST LISTEN. AFTER THAT YOU DECIDE IF YOU
JUST WANT TO BE A WITNESS OF WHAT I'M GOING TO SAY OR ACT
ACCORDINGLY TO WHAT IS POSSIBLE FOR YOU TO DO.
>> OKAY. SO THE 15 NEXT THROUGH THE
15,000 MILES ARE COVERED ON THE ROAD TO INSPECT THE COUNTRY
AND THE LAST TWO OF TWO MONTHS. >> AND WHAT DOES TO ME TO GIVE
YOU A GIFT OF A GIFT FOR YOU KNOW, DON'T CELEBRATE TOO FAST
BECAUSE IT'S WRAPPED INTO AN ULTIMATUM.
>> SO YOU HAVE UNTIL JULY 1ST WHICH YOU SENT JERRY ON THE
CATHOLIC CALENDAR. >> WHOA.
COINCIDENCE TO STOP THINKING DOWN ALL THE 5G NEFARIOUS
DOORBELLS THAT YOU INSTALLED INSTALLED ALL OVER THE COUNTRY
SIDE OF THIS COUNTRY. I DON'T KNOW.
>> IT SEEMS NEFARIOUS. YOU KNOW IT WHICH IS EXACTLY
WHY YOU PUT THESE UGLY STUFF SOMETIMES UNDER 50FT.
>> ARE YOU AGAINST THE PEOPLE DONATION?
>> HE DIDN'T ASK ANYONE. THAT'S NO GOOD.
OKAY. WHEN YOU START TAKING THEM DOWN
STEP BY STEP FIRST IN PLACES OF LESS THAN 70,000 PEOPLE.
>> OKAY, WE'LL SEE FOR THE REST.
SECOND THAT YOU'RE GOING TO HAVE TO EAT FOR BREAKFAST.
YOU ARE ON SCENE. THAT IS JUST DONE FOR YOUR FATE
. WHAT WORKS THAT YOU PUT ALSO
ALL OVER THE COUNTRY TO PEOPLE OFF BUT YOU DECIDE THE DRESSING
I WILL SUGGEST LUNCH TALK TO YOU SOONER AFTER THAT WE TAKE
DOWN THIS TOWARDS OURSELVES. ARE YOU STILL GOING TO HAVE TO
CLEAN THEM UP? IT'S YOUR GAGA NOT THE PEOPLE'S
. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENT.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. FOR THE RECORD MY NAME IS CHRIS
WARD KLEIN. I WILL SPEAK ABOUT SERGEANT
KLEIN OF THE UNITED STATES MARINE CORPS.
FOR SEVERAL MONTHS NOW I'VE BEEN TELLING SAN FRANCISCO THAT
THERE WOULD BE VIOLENCE AND THERE WOULD BE RIOTS
AND THAT IS BECAUSE POLICE DEPARTMENT OFFICIALS ARE NOT
ARRESTING THE RIGHT PEOPLE. SO PEOPLE HAVE TO BE CALLED
IN TO ARREST THESE PEOPLE. YOU WILL BE SEEING THAT PLAY
OUT OVER THE NEXT COUPLE OF DAYS, COUPLE OF WEEKS.
THINGS WILL PROBABLY GET WORSE BEFORE THEY GET BETTER.
SIGNAL INTELLIGENCE IS NOT NEVER A GOOD THING WHEN
GRANTING ACCESS TO THIRD PARTIES SUCH AS FOREIGN
COUNTRIES UNIVERSITIES AND OTHER CORPORATIONS THAT
SHOULD NOT HAVE ACCESS. OVER THE LAST TWO DAY TWO DAYS
I WE HAVE IDENTIFIED VEHICLES PARKED OUTSIDE OF YOUR FIRE
DEPARTMENT. THEY'RE PLACED THERE TO REVERSE
ENGINEER SIGNAL INTELLIGENCE TO CAUSE VIOLENCE IN L.A.,
COLORADO, BOSTON AND VICE VERSA.
IT COMES BACK THE SAME WAY. THAT IS WHAT IS HAPPENING.
PEOPLE ARE CAUSING OR INFLUENCING THE VIOLENCE.
>> IT HAS TO STOP. >> 700 MARINES WERE DEPLOYED TO
L.A. AND FOR ONE REASON TO BRING PEACE AND TO FIX THE
COMMUNICATION EQUIPMENT TO SQUASH THE VIOLENCE BY SIMPLY
CHANGING THE WORK COMMUNIQUE ATION SYSTEM.
THAT'S ALL IT TAKES. I WE INVITE SAN FRANCISCO TO BE
PART OF A CLASS ACTION LAWSUIT VERSUS STATE SPONSORED
TERRORISM NAMING SEVERAL COUNTRIES TO CLAIM OVER $5
BILLION IN UNCLAIMED DAMAGES. WE NEED THAT MONEY.
WE NEED THIS PEACE. WE NEED UNITY AND COMMUNITY
AGAIN. IF YOU OR OTHERS GAVE OUT
ACCESS TO THE UNIVERSITIES, TO CORPORATIONS OR TO A FOREIGN
COUNTRY, YOU NEED TO CEASE AND DESIST IMMEDIATELY.
ARE YOU RISK GETTING ARRESTED? IT IS THAT VERY SIMPLE.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. >> LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER. CAN YOU READ THAT FOR ME?
OH, SHANE MICHAEL, SLEEP HERE. I WAS STRANGLED FOR 35 MINUTES
IN SAN FRANCISCO BUT I ONLY HAVE TWO MINUTES TO SPEAK.
HOW COULD YOU POSSIBLY UNDERSTAND HOW TO FIX SOMETHING
WHEN THE ABUSE LASTED LONGER THAN YOU WILL EVER ALLOW TO
LISTEN? I'VE GOT A COURT DATE TO ATTEND
ACCOMPLISHING NO CHANGE. THANKS TO CHRISTINA TULLOCH
SOMEONE THAT I WOULD DEFINE AS A FOR ATTEMPTING TO REFUSE MY
CONSTITUTIONAL RIGHTS. IN ADDITION TO SOME OFFICERS
THAT I WOULD DEFINE AS PIGS FOR DOING THE SAME TO SILENCE
ABUSES I'LL BE SPEAKING UP TODAY.
LAST TIME I WAS HERE I WAS GETTING LAUGHED AT BY THE
INDIVIDUAL NEXT TO SPEAK IN LINE.
WHO THOUGHT IT WAS FUNNY WHEN I TOLD HER I HAD MONTHS OF MY
FREEDOM STOLEN FOR TAKING DOWN A CURTAIN WITH ON IT WHILE SHE
ABOUT TRUMP STEALING HER RIGHTS FOR WANTING TO STILL BE AN
IGNORANT LIKELY NOT LIVING WITH STAPLED TO HER WALL OR
BEING ARRESTED SHOULD SHE CHOOSE TO TAKE IT DOWN.
YOU HAVEN'T HEARD A PEEP FROM MR. LEARY'S ACCOUNTABILITY
AGENDA THOUGH, HAVE YOU? USE.
THIS IS SAN FRANCISCO PRIDE. PRIDE IN THE IGNORANCE THAT
WANTS TO CONTINUE TO DEFINE ME AS A TERRORIST WHEN I SPEAK UP
TO ABUSES AMONG MANY SUCH AS SOMEONE GETTING SEXUALLY
HARASSED BY OFFICERS WHO GET TO PARTAKE IN STRANGLING ME WITH A
SEAT BELT FOR STICKING UP FOR THEM WITHOUT CONSEQUENCE WHILE
I'M ALREADY FULLY RESTRAINED. I HAVE YET TO SPEAK OF THE
SEXUAL ASSAULTS BY THE COMMUNITY BUT I'D LIKE TO STATE
HAPPY PRIDE TO AMERICA OVER ANY ATTEMPTING TO SILENCE THE
SEXUAL ABUSE AND EXPLOITATION THEY HAVE CHOSEN TO TAKE PART
IN THAT MANY OF THEM STILL ATTEMPT TO SILENCE.
BLACK, WHITE, BROWN AND YELLOW GAY AND STRAIGHT REPUBLICAN
AND DEMOCRAT THEIR AND EVERY RACE.
I THINK WE'D ALL DO GOOD. UNDERSTANDING THAT MOTTO VERSUS
INDIVIDUAL. REGULARLY PUSHED BY THOSE THAT
SWEEP OTHERS LIVES UNDER THE RUG.
FOR THE DESTRUCTION OF A COUNTRY THEY NEVER WANTED TO BE
A PART OF. ONLY CONQUER.
WE'VE GOT AN $840 MILLION POLICE BUDGET WITH MORE THAN
THREE QUARTERS OF OUR OFFICERS NOT EVEN RESIDENTS OF SAN
FRANCISCO. I THINK I UNDERSTAND THE
PROBLEM QUITE WELL DESPITE BEING LABELED DELUSIONAL BY
JOHN JULIAN HOWARD WHO ASKED ME HOW MUCH OF A MARTYR I'M
WILLING TO BECOME FOR THE SYSTEM AS I HAVE MY CLOTHES CUT
OFF OF ME AND BE TOLD I'M GOING TO HAVE MY RAPED WITH A
BROOMSTICK BEFORE BEING PUT UNCONSCIOUS?
IS THIS JUSTICE TO YOU? >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
EXCEPT FOR THE CURSE WORD. MRS. BROWN, WERE YOU GOING TO
GO NEXT? OR.
OKAY, LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
WELCOME. >> UM, CAN I HAVE SOMEONE PICK
UP SOMETHING I'D LIKE TO HAND OUT TO THE BOARD?
CERTAINLY. I'LL HAVE THE SERGEANT AT ARMS
COME HELP YOU. THANK.
>> OKAY. HELLO.
>> FIRST I NOTICE THAT AT THE PRIDE FLAG RAISING CEREMONY
THIS YEAR AS OPPOSED TO THE THREE PREVIOUS YEARS THAT I
CHECKED, THERE WAS NO TRANSGENDER FLAG ALONGSIDE THE
THE RAINBOW FLAG. >> SO SHAME AND ALL YOU
CISGENDER PEOPLE WHO PARTOOK IN THAT CEREMONY AND WERE OKAY
WITH TRANS ERASURE AND THE TRANSGENDER SANCTUARY CITY
AND A TRANSGENDER SANCTUARY STATE.
>> SECOND I CAME FROM THE PROTESTS OVER AT MONTGOMERY
STREET WITH ICE. >> I CALL IT KIDNAPING PEOPLE.
>> THERE WAS A CALL PUT OUT TO SHOW UP BECAUSE THAT WAS
HAPPENING. I SHOWED UP EARLY AND I
WITNESSED ONE OF THESE KIDNAPINGS.
>> IT WAS HORRIFYING. >> IT WAS AN UNMARKED VAN.
THESE AGENTS WERE MASKED IN PLAIN CLOTHES.
IF YOU WERE A PERSON WALKING BY ON THE STREETS YOU WOULDN'T
KNOW IT WAS A GOVERNMENT. ANYTHING HAPPENING?
IT WOULD JUST LOOK LIKE A CIVILIAN KIDNAPING.
>> WE WERE NOT ALLOWED TO SPEAK TO THE PERSON THAT WAS BEING
KIDNAPED. >> THE VEHICLE WAS VERY
AGGRESSIVELY DRIVEN INTO PROTESTERS.
I REALLY THOUGHT SOMEONE WAS GOING TO GET RUN OVER.
>> I, I SHOWED UP THINKING I COULD JUST HAND OUT SOME STUPID
RED CARDS WITH IMMIGRANT RIGHTS AND AFTER SEEING THAT IT'S LIKE
THAT. BUT THOSE PIECES OF PAPER.
>> AND I'M SORRY IF THAT'S PUT YOU AND IT WAS NOTHING
IN COMPARISON TO WHAT I WITNESSED HAPPEN.
I SAW MOTHERS AND FATHERS WITH THEIR CHILDREN GO INTO THIS ICE
COURT AND I WAS AFRAID LIKE ARE THEY GOING TO COME OUT NEXT OR
KIDNAPED? >> IF YOU KIDS ASKING ME
IN ENGLISH HOW TO OPEN THE DOOR TO THE COURT AND I HAD TO SHOW
THEM BECAUSE THEIR PARENTS DIDN'T KNOW ENGLISH.
LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE.
>> WHEN YOU LOOK IN THE MIRROR, TELL ME WHAT DO YOU SEE?
>> DO YOU WALK WITH THE GIANTS OR DO YOU CATCH A FLEA?
>> WE ARE NOTHING MORE BUT WHAT WE THINK WE ARE.
>> I'M ASKING YOU TO BE HEROES .
I'VE BEEN TORTURED FOR SIX YEARS.
VICTIM OF VIOLENCE ILLEGALLY OR EVICTED.
I WAS THE VICTIM, NOT THE PERPETRATOR.
>> ALL MY HEALING ARTS AND SCHOOL FOR THE KIDS.
ROBBED IN A WELL-OILED MACHINE PUT IN WITH RAPISTS
AND KILLERS. >> UNBELIEVABLE BULLY
TRAUMATIZED WITH FIVE BROKEN BONES FROM VIOLENCE.
>> AND THEN THIS SPRING KIDNAPED TORTURED AGAIN FOR THE
SECOND TIME I ASK YOU TO MAKE PEOPLE WITH EDUCATION
AND INTEGRITY. >> NO CRIMINAL RECORDS.
ELDERS AND NOT TO BE ALLOWED TO BE TORTURED AND KIDNAPED.
I WAS ALSO TORTURED AND KIDNAPED BECAUSE I WAS
KIDNAPED AFTER ONE VIOLENT ASSAULT BY THE PARAMEDICS WHO
WOULDN'T LET ME NOT GO TO THE HOSPITAL.
AT THE HOSPITAL I WAS BEATEN FOR SEVEN HOURS AS AN EPILEPTIC
AND DISABLED PERSON WITH HIDDEN DISABILITIES.
>> I FIGHT PROBLEMS ALL THE TIME RACIALLY XENOPHOBIC.
>> THERE IS NO JUSTICE. THERE ARE REWARDING
AND REWARDING BAD BAD BEHAVIOR .
NOW THEY'RE SAYING IT'S MY FAULT AND ON ME THAT I CAN'T
MOVE IN TIME THAT I WASN'T ABLE TO WITH MY HEAD NOT BEING ABLE
TO SPEAK BECAUSE PEOPLE CRASH MUSIC OR PEOPLE ARE DOWN THE
HALL AND THREATENING TO CHOP OFF HEADS AND KILL ME.
THERE ARE KIDNAPINGS GOING ON. YES THERE ARE.
THERE'S UNBELIEVABLE NOT RECOGNITION OF PEOPLE'S NEED
FOR SAFETY AND TO CHANGE THE STATUS QUO.
>> THAT HAS NOT CHANGED SINCE THE GOLD RUSH.
100 AND 50 YEARS OF LANDLORD SUPREMACY JAILS AND I MEAN NOT
JAILS COURTYARDS THAT ARE KANGAROO COURTS.
>> NO ABILITY, NO HELP. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. >> LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER. >> I MEAN YOU CAN COME BACK
NEXT WEEK. YEAH, I WAS BORN IN MILWAUKEE.
I'M OF AN AGE WHERE IF I HAD BEEN BORN IN VIETNAM I PROBABLY
WOULD HAVE DIED FIGHTING FOR MY COUNTRY.
AND IF I HAD BEEN BORN FIVE YEARS EARLIER THAN THAT THAN I
WAS BORN, I PROBABLY WOULD HAVE WOUND UP SERVING IN OUR
MILITARY KILLING THE PEOPLE WHO ARE DYING FOR THEIR COUNTRY.
THERE'S BEEN IT'S BEEN SOME UPS AND DOWNS IN THE TIMES.
I WANT TO SPEAK ABOUT SOMETHING PRAGMATIC.
MY NAME'S IRA DUFFY. I LIVE IN A NEIGHBORHOOD NEARBY
HERE. ONE OF THE OTHER SUPERVISORS
TALKED ABOUT IT WHEN THE TAYLOR STREET CONSTRUCTION WAS
COMPLETED. THEY PUT SOME FLOURISHES ON IT
SOME FLOWERS, SOME BENCHES. >> AND BEFORE THE CONSTRUCTION
THAT BLOCK OF TAYLOR STREET WAS THE NARROWEST SIDEWALK IN THE
DOWNTOWN AREA AND WAS VERY DIFFICULT TO GET GET BY IT.
AND NOW WITH ALL THESE FURNITURE IT IS NOW ONCE AGAIN
THE MOST NARROW WITH SIDEWALK ALTHOUGH THEY MADE IT LARGER.
AS IT STANDS NOW IT'S THE NARROWEST SIDEWALK IN THE
DOWNTOWN AREA. IT'S VERY DIFFICULT TO GET
AROUND AND IT IS AN ISSUE OF CONGREGATION OF HOMELESS
PEOPLE. SO MAYBE THE OVERALL PICTURE IS
DOING BETTER BUT CERTAINLY THAT BLOCK OF TAYLOR STREET AND YOU
KNOW, I COULD USE SOME SOME SOME RADICAL RECONSTRUCTION
DECONSTRUCTION. >> THANK YOU.
NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE. IF YOU ARE HERE TO PROVIDE
GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT TO THE BOARD IT'S YOUR TURN TO LINE UP
ON YOUR RIGHT HAND SIDE. OTHERWISE THESE WILL BE OUR
LAST TWO SPEAKERS. >> WELCOME TO ASK A QUESTION.
YES. >> WELL I'M HERE BECAUSE IT
KNOWS THAT AT SAN FRANCISCO LAW THAT YOU DON'T LET THE POLICE
CHECK THE DATABASE. AND I CAN'T SAY TOO MUCH
BECAUSE I'M STANDING HERE AND I'M NERVOUS
AND UNFORTUNATELY I NEED TO FIND OUT HOW CAN I GO ABOUT
PUTTING THAT ON THE VOTING FOR NOVEMBER BECAUSE THEY CAN'T
CHECK THE DATABASE. SO I DON'T WANT TO GO NO FOR
SAYING WHATEVER I HAVE TO SAY BECAUSE PEOPLE'S WATCHING ME ON
TV. SO AFTER THIS OVER CAN SOMEONE
COME TALK TO ME? >> CERTAINLY.
PAM, IF YOU HAVE A SEAT ON THE FRONT ROW I'LL HAVE STAFF COME
OVER AND TAKE YOUR INFORMATION FROM YOU.
ALL RIGHT. THANK YOU.
RIGHT, SIR. COME ON UP.
IF THERE ISN'T ANYONE ELSE, THIS WILL BE OUR LAST SPEAKER
UNLESS YOU GET UP NOW. OKAY.
OKAY. THANK YOU, MS..
>> BROWN. WE'LL HEAR FROM YOU NEXT.
UNFORTUNATELY SOME OF US NEED TO SIT.
WE CAN'T STAND TOO LONG. I HAVE VERTIGO.
MY DOG IS NAMED SLY AND HIS FULL NAME IS SLY.
THE FAMILY STONE ARE AND I THINK THAT THIS BOARD AND THIS
COMMUNITY ARE TO RECOGNIZE THE RECENT DEATH OF SLY WHO WAS THE
LEADER OF SLY AND THE FAMILY STONE AND NOTICED THAT THE
GROUP COMPRISED OF MEN, WOMEN, BLACKS, WHITES, LATINOS,
EVERYBODY IN THE CITY. THE OTHER COMMENT I WANTED TO
MAKE IS ON THIS THE CITY MALL THE BEST IDEA I'VE HEARD SO FAR
THAT WAS FLOATED IS WHY DON'T YOU TURN THE NORDSTROM AREA
INTO A SUPPER CLUB, SOMETHING LIKE THAT.
IT WAS ONCE PROPOSED TO BE MANAGED BY A LAS VEGAS
ENTREPRENEUR MANAGER AND THAT SEEMED TO ME TO BE THE GREATEST
IDEA OF ALL. IT WOULD BRING LIFE DOWN TO THE
MID-MARKET CENTER ANYWAY, THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS .
ALL RIGHT, MS.. BROWN, WELCOME.
>> I NEED FOR HIM TO FIX THIS AND SO GO TV AND THE PROJECTOR
,PLEASE. THANK YOU.
WHERE YOU START MY TIME. OH, OKAY.
OKAY. UM, THANK YOU.
I JUST WANT TO THANK EVERYONE TO MOVE ON YESTERDAY AT THE
RULES COMMITTEE FOR A PASSING THE THE LEGISLATION AT THE
RULES COMMITTEE. >> I BRING THIS BECAUSE WHY I'M
STANDING HERE I'M TALKING ABOUT ABOUT THE LACK OF REWARDS ARE
BEING PAID OUT IN A DECADE AND I BRING THESE BECAUSE I'VE
BEEN ASKING FOR THIS FOR LIKE YEARS NOW HERE'S ANOTHER ONE
THAT WAS BROUGHT UP AT THE POLICE COMMISSION ABOUT THE
REWARDS AND INFORMATION. >> HERE'S ANOTHER ONE.
THIS WAS IN 2022. THIS IS 2024 ABOUT REWARDS FOR
UNSOLVED AND COLD CASE HOMICIDES.
>> SO ON ON JANUARY 17TH AND 24TH OF THIS MONTH WILL AT
THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS ON TUESDAY I'M I'M PLEADING THAT
YOU PASS THIS OF THIS LEGISLATION INTO LAW ON THE
24TH ON THE 17TH AND THE 24TH I BRING THE PICTURES OF OF MY SON
WHO WAS MURDERED AUGUST 26TH, 1426 TO THIS DAY HIS CASE HAS
BEEN SOLVED. >> HERE IS OTHER UNSOLVED
HOMICIDES TOO THAT THESE CASES HAVEN'T BEEN SOLVED.
HERE ARE OTHER HOMICIDES THAT THESE CASES HAVEN'T BEEN
SOLVED. >> HERE ARE OTHER HOMICIDES
THAT THESE CASES HAVE SOLVED. >> MOTHERS LIKE MYSELF ARE
ASKING FOR JUSTICE. SO I PRAY THAT ON THE 17TH
AND THE 24TH THAT THIS LEGISLATION BE PASSED.
>> THIS IS WHAT THE PERPETRATORS LEFT ME WITH A
LIFELESS BODY MY SON THIS LAYING IN A CASKET THIS IS WHAT
I HAVE TO THINK ABOUT EVERY DAY THAT MY SON IS LAYING ON A
GURNEY LIFELESS I STAND HERE AS A MOTHER OF A CHILD THAT WAS
FULL OF LIFE AND NOW I KNOW HE WAS MY ONLY SON.
>> THANK THANK YOU, MR. BROWN. ARE ARE THERE ANY OTHER MEMBERS
OF THE PUBLIC WHO WOULD LIKE TO ADDRESS THE BOARD?
>> ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT. ALL RIGHT.
>> PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED AND MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO
OUR FOR ADOPTION OF THAT COMMITTEE REFERENCE AGENDA
ITEMS 36 AND 37 ITEM 36 AND 37 WERE INTRODUCED FOR ADOPTION
WITHOUT REFERENCE TO COMMITTEE. A UNANIMOUS VOTE IS REQUIRED
FOR ADOPTION OF A RESOLUTION ON FIRST READING TODAY.
ALTERNATIVELY A MEMBER MAY REQUIRE A RESOLUTION TO GO TO
COMMITTEE. >> ALEXX DOES ANYONE WANT TO
SEVER ANY ITEMS? I DO NOT SEE ANY SO.
>> MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL AND ITEMS
36 AND 37 SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR
EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON ALL RIGHT
WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN
EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO
ENGARDIO EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
AND SUPERVISOR MANDEL MAN HI MANDELL MAN I THERE ARE TEN
EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED AND THE
MOTION IS APPROVED. >> MADAM CLERK DO WE HAVE ANY
IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS? I HAVE NO IMPERATIVES TO
REPORT, MR. PRESIDENT. >> ALL RIGHT.
THEN, MADAM CLERK UH, COULD YOU READ PLEASE READ THE
IN MEMORIAM. >> YESTERDAY'S MEETING WILL BE
ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUAL
BILLS ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR CHAN FOR THE LATE MR. SHAWN
O'NEAL MCGREW ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR CHIN NOTED HERE IS
SUPERVISOR WALTON AND CHAN AND A MOTION MADE BY THE BOARD
PRESIDENT TO BE ON BEHALF OF THE ENTIRE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
FOR THE LATE MISS LOUISA BLUE THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
I THINK THAT BRINGS US TO THE END OF OUR AGENDA DO WE HAVE
ANY FURTHER BUSINESS BEFORE US TODAY?
>> THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS FOR TODAY.
>> WELL THEN WE ARE ADJOURNED